ADAM BALDWIN: So what I wanna know is,
in this opening title sequence
whose brilliant idea was this with
the "whoosh" and the... 'Cause...
JOSS WHEDON: What?
The making of...
With the going into the
gray and everything like...
Oh, come on! That was...
Whose idea was that?
That was the first thing
I wanted to do.
I didn't even have a story. I just pitched,
"Can we just move past the logo?"
NATHAN FILLLON: Have we started?
We started? We've started.
Okay, well,
I remember you bringing this
down to the set,
then we were watching this
over and over and over again.
(IN FALSETTO)
So exciting.
I know! We had
a special effect.
RON GLASS: But when do
we introduce ourselves?
We're going to. And this is
sort of like a pre-credit sequence.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
Okay,
let's start with me. Let's start with me.
(WHISPERING)
Which one am I?
SUMMER GLAU: You're Joss.
Joss is the boss.
I'm Joss Whedon,
and I totally made this movie.
And I'm Summer,
and I'm in it. Hi.
Well, I'm Ron,
and I'm sort of in it, too.
(GLAU LAUGHING)
I'm Adam. I'm Jayne,
the guy in this.
I'm Nathan Fillion,
and I'm in it the most.
(WHISPERING) Score!
GLASS: Thank you, Joss.
WHEDON:
Well, thanks for coming.
BALDWIN: You're great. I mean,
thank you for letting me be in it.
Oh, you know, it was a vote.
(ALL LAUGHING)
FILLLON: Joss came to me and he said,
"We got to kill somebody."
And I said, "Ron and Adam."
(GLASS LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: Now, young
Summer in this is
a kid who went to
dance class with my kids.
So when you overdubbed her voice
with Summer's voice, she was heartbroken.
GLAU: Oh, wow,
I didn't know that.
WHEDON: Yeah. Well,
that's what I was going for.
One of the things I like to do,
besides making films, is make little girls cry.
(ALL LAUGHING) And you can
only hide under a bridge for so long.
Eventually, you have to, like,
get out there and make films with them.
And then dub them with Summer.
GLASS: I really liked...
I liked her a lot.
Hunter was great but it just...
Oh, Tamara? Tamara's wonderful.
BALDWIN: She's lovely.
GLASS: Oh, I love Hunter.
WHEDON: But it's just...
It makes the connection easier.
You know, it's hard. There's a lot of
connections for the audience to make.
BALDWIN: Summer still has that child's voice,
so it's very childlike.
Well, Summer was like...
GLASS: The first really big surprise.
FILLLON: This was
the first day.
BALDWIN: This was the
very first day. GLAU: Yes.
FILLLON: You took pictures.
WHEDON: Yes, I took pictures.
That was. You guys stopped... And
we did some costume testing thing,
so we had Morena
and people walking by.
GLASS: Was that fun? That
must've been fun the first day, huh?
BALDWIN: It was great. You should've been there,
Ron.
(GLASS LAUGHING) Oh, my God,
we had so much fun this day.
WHEDON: We did 33 setups.
I remember 'cause...
Cause after...
At the end of the day,
Sean was like, "So,
this is different from the TV show exactly how?"
'Cause we just... 33! Boom,
boom, boom. With Jack Green!
Yes, that's what
I tried to explain.
FILLLON: And we actually filmed Ariel there,
that was the prison.
GLAU: Was it, really?
FILLLON: Yeah. In Ariel. Yeah.
WHEDON: That's where we filmed.
That's where you guys were running around.
Yeah, this is in, actually,
the very room that you guys ran through,
and, yeah...
I talked about that on the
other commentary. Hello!
(GLAU CHUCKLES)
WHEDON: But the other
commentary didn't have us.
(WHEDON LAUGHS) GLAU: No.
And it wouldn't stay on. It kept falling off.
That's right, she'd be, like,
moaning and it was, like,
terrifying. The thing would go...
(GIBBERING)
It'd just kind of
drip off her head.
BALDWIN:
Is Sean usually happy?
Sean?
He's constantly happy.
He just doesn't like to share that
with you. He doesn't want you to know.
He knows you'll
use it against him.
FILLLON: He's so guarded when it comes to you,
Adam. BALD WIN.” Totally right.
(GLAU CHUCKLES)
She always did love to dance.
(MACHINERY WHIRRING)
(GLASS SHATTERING)
River, it's Simon.
FILLLON: We didn't do
the first Serenity... Um...
What do you call these,
commentaries?
WHEDON: Uh-huh.
This is a commentary.
And now here we are,
doing the special edition.
Is this what this is called?
That's right.
Special edition.
We are the future of
commentary unless...
BALDWIN: And the movie is where?
The movie's up there.
Yeah, look.
We're in a box.
FILLLON: Yeah, looking good, sir.
WHEDON: We're in a little box
and the movie's... Yeah.
They're big.
FILLLON: These guys were good.
GLASS: Who's that guy?
Where are they going?
Why are they running?
WHEDON: You did see
the film, didn't you?
You know, by the way,
I watched it a couple months ago.
GLASS: I watched it
almost an the way through.
I had never watched it since
the 9,000 fan screenings we did.
FILLLON: This is March, 2007.
We filmed this, what?
2004?
Yeah. I think so.
I'm not great with
dates. FILLLON: Nor am I.
How do you feel looking
back at this and watching it?
What's going through your mind? Joss Whedon,
let's start with you.
What's going through
my mind? Um...
Well, I'll tell you,
I watched it a couple of months ago,
you know, without us all
talking over it and stuff.
And I noticed something that
I thought was really interesting.
All the stuff that I totally took for granted,
that I loved,
I wasn't really sure
that I liked that much.
And the stuff I wasn't sure about,
I thought worked like gangbusters.
Really?
All the talking.
Man, I mean,
you know we cutout half the dialogue. Yeah.
How do I have time
to write that much?
I'm like the most... I'm like Stephen King,
I'm like Dostoevsky.
There's so much talking.
Everybody's talking.
They're all talking.
Are you saying you look
back at this film with regret?
I'm saying there's
a lot of talking.
I'm saying it's sweet,
and I like the movie.
But sometimes I'm like, "Wow, Joss, you
really like to hear yourself type, don't you?"
That's Why the girls like
the sci-fi movie, Serenity,
because there's
a lot of talking.
Oh, okay, okay.
Summer?
Yes? When you look back,
any feelings, any emotions?
What are you thinking about
when you're watching your...
WHEDON: Have you finally
learned human emotions?
GLAU: I still...
(GLAU LAUGHS)
BALDWIN: How many pages
was the first draft?
WHEDON: The first draft
was 190 pages.
FILLION: And atypical
script should be?
Typical script, 120.
GLASS: Oh, that's what happened.
Yes! Those were 70 pages of you.
(ALL LAUGHING) Riffing and joking,
a little soft-shoe, man.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
Um, and Alan had a line.
No. It was, yeah... You know,
everybody lived,
and everything was resolved,
and every plot point was brought up
that was ever in the show.
It was season two,
first draft was season two,
so I winnowed it down from that.
GLASS: You know, the question that just keeps
coming up over and over and over and over is
people want to know if! know
What Book's background was.
Uh-huh.
Sometime before this is over,
perhaps you can... I should tell you?
You know...
GLAU: Clue us all in.
It's... Your birthday's
coming up,
and I got you a back story.
BALDWIN: So wait a minute.
If the 190 page script was season two,
what was the second half of season one?
Oh, I see what you're saying. That
was gonna be a lot of gobbledygook.
Car chases. FILLLON: A lot
more setup for season two.
WHEDON: No, but the
discovery of Miranda
was always meant to be
the end of season two for me.
So that's why I sort of think of it that
way. I was gonna draw it out for two years.
And then Jim and Pam
were gonna get together.
No, wait. No,
that's the wrong show, I'm sorry.
Um, 30, Adam,
your feelings three years on?
I still think Jayne
has a crush on lnara.
You know, we got...
You gotta get past this.
I think it would've worked out.
No,
because the underlying tension there
with Mai and... You know that this
is one of the first things he pitched.
'Cause you know,
when we all sat down at rehearsal
to talk about
what everything meant,
he's all up in his weapons,
talked about his weapons,
in a sexual fashion that! think
would've embarrassed Animal Mother.
I mean, honestly,
that was really an eye-opener for me.
And then, started going
with the Inara crush,
and this was a thing.
FILLLON: Only after
he had met Morena.
Oh, we will... I mean,
don't get me wrong.
It's not like...
None of us is suffering.
BALDWIN: It was just a way of giving me,
sort of,
this motivation in any scene
where there was the three of them.
I don't know,
'cause I think she's a perfect woman for Jayne.
FILLLON: (LAUGHING)
I agree. I'm laughing.
That's agreement laughter.
WHEDON: She thinks that, too.
BALDWIN: I don't think she agrees,
but I figure I can sway her.
FILLLON: Do you ever... Do you
guys ever look back with, "Ah! Yes."
We just kind of wrapped up
that TV season that we kind of...
The TV experience that was
cut dramatically short, I believe.
Do you ever look back and go,
"What could've been?"
WHEDON: Wait, those are
two different things.
One of them was, "Ah, yes." And one of them was,
"What could've been?"
So which one do you experience?
FILLLON: "Ah, yes,
What could've been."
Oh, that's cheating.
Yeah, thanks.
What?
I look at this and I say,
"Thank God," number one,
that we were able
to make the movie.
I had a really good time.
I think we deserved it.
I think so, too.
I think it's a nice piece.
It's a really nice piece. It's some
of my favorite work I've ever done.
And I think it's some of your best work,
Jess, and I'd like to take credit for it.
I think It's among my top
three films that I've directed.
(GLAU GIGGLES)
FILLLON: How many films
have you directed?
I'm sorry?
I mean, could be you'll
see later that I'm right.
Good.
'Cause it's all
downhill from here.
No more of that camera
movement, just talk.
Um, I have both, too.
I have a sense of closure,
I love the film.
You know...
GLASS: I have a sense of closure.
(WHEDON LAUGHING)
It's coming up.
(ALL LAUGHING)
FILLLON: Oh, funny 'cause
he's dead. Good times.
GLASS: Okay, I'll stop. WHEDON: No,
no, no. It doesn't get old.
And the fact is, yeah,
no... You know what?
That was really, really,
really, hard for both of us.
Harder for you,
but hard for both of us.
And there was a time, you know,
I hope you don't mind me
saying, when you were like,
"I'm not sure. I'm not
sure I can go back there
"to be this guy for this short a time,"
and it was too painful.
Not just, you know, like,
"I've been short-changed,"
but because of Book,
which I respect completely.
The thing I loved was that
it made me sort of go back
and redo his whole scene.
I rewrote the whole scene with Mal
to really, you know, let Book
embody the themes in a much
more simple and straightforward way,
and it changed both the
scenes and it changed the way...
It's like, you know, the line,
"What Shepherd Book told me."
"If you can't do something smart,
do something right."
Originally, that was
his crazy grandma.
Little things like that to put in to
just remember this guy's a part of it
and seed him throughout.
And I kind of had the
same thing with Morena
who, after you, probably suffered the most,
more in the editing process.
But, you know, she said,
"I feel like I get lost,"
when she saw one of the many,
many, many, cuts that I did.
And we ended up putting back
the painting of the ship
in the montage at the
end because of that.
And the way you guys need
to protect your characters
and all have crushes on Inara,
which was just weird for you but,
you know, it didn't really bother anyone.
FILLLON: Worked for me.
BALDWIN: What's not to crush?
WHEDON: I was having a talk
with an actor about that.
He's like,
"I'm just too protective of the character."
And I'm like,
"That's how it works."
I am, obviously.
I adore these characters,
and obviously,
I'm fond of you guys 'cause look what we did.
It's not enough.
Just get us on the ground!
That part will happen
pretty definitely.
We're gonna explode?
I don't wanna explode.
Jayne,
how many weapons you plan on taking?
You only got two arms.
I just get excitable
as to choice. Like to
have my options open.
I don't plan on any shooting
taking place during this job.
BALDWIN: Can you talk about how
complicated this tracking shot was?
WHEDON: Oh, it was a piece of
cake. We got this in, what, three takes?
Oh, no. it was 46.
That's right.
It was 30 takes upstairs,
16 takes downstairs.
FILLLON: And then we had
to loop the entire thing.
And then we had to
loop the entire thing.
This was also a thing
that I'm proud of.
I have an entire set
that actually shakes.
And I go in it with a Steadicam.
(ALL LAUGHING) So it
takes away an the shake,
thereby rendering
the whole thing...
You know, we could've
done that with five guys,
just below the table instead.
FILLLON: Jewel Staite. Let's talk about
Jewel for a second 'cause she's not here.
WHEDON: I probably
should...
I looked at the commentary and I'm
just crushing on Jewel for a lot of it.
I love the way she plays Kaylee.
GLAU: Yeah, she's amazing.
FILLLON: Let me do it
for a While, then.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
She's such a sparkly
little girl.
She's such a wonderful,
kind of a free spirit in real life,
but that Kaylee,
I'm totally in love with Kaylee.
Bit of a rockety ride.
I find Jewel was always,
like, "Whatever."
Like she had this attitude, "Really,
you wanna do that? Whatever."
And then, on came Kaylee.
Like, Jewel's such a pro,
and not that she didn't care,
but she had this sort of... She'd always
look at you when you gave her a note like,
"You're a little slow,
aren't you?"
(GLAU LAUGHS)
And then, she'd do it,
and it would be beautiful,
and she'd incorporate everything
with her heart and delightful.
But I loved the way
she switched Kaylee on.
GLASS: She was always... The thing I
observed about her was that she always seemed,
on the outside, you know,
it's like her face,
like, it just didn't...
Like it didn't...
It was very kind of classic.
She didn't, like, seem like...
But I could always tell
that inside there was...
it was like going
a mile a minute.
You know, though outside it just seemed
like there was nothing going on, you know.
WHEDON: That's how Michael Caine
described great acting, by the way.
FILLLON: Really?
Yeah.
Exactly that.
GLASS: That's where I got that from.
- Nice. Stealing from Caine.
- BALDWIN: I thought he said, "Don't blink."
That, too, which you did.
Yeah, Nathan, you blinked.
BALDWIN: I never blink.
I try never to blink.
(RUMBLING)
Honestly, Doctor,
I think we may really crash this time anyway.
FILLLON: Now I'm just
watching the movie.
WHEDON: I know, I know.
Well, that's gonna happen.
Sometimes we're just
gonna watch the movie,
but people get to enjoy
us watching the movie.
GLASS: You know what? I always...
I always wanted to cook more.
Yeah, I love cooking.
I love cooking.
I loved it on the show. GLASS: in real life,
of course I don't cook at a”, but...
Well, you're an actor,
you wanna explore new worlds.
FILLLON: You mean, as Book,
you mean? GLASS: Yeah.
WHEDON: Well, that's some of the stuff that,
you know, from the show.
You know,
my sense of closure that I got, great.
My not-sense of closure?
"Movie different from show,"
is all the little things that, you know...
The process of editing the
movie was taking everything out.
And sometimes, you know,
that's great.
Sometimes, you know,
I did overwrite.
And sometimes
the moment was there.
But the great thing about
a show is you can say,
"I really wanna see
Book cooking."
And somewhere you know
you're gonna get to that.
Somewhere you can
find a place for that.
Because I love that.
I love food.
I love anything that's
tactile in this world so much.
I always want people to be doing stuff,
which is lucky,
because there's always stuff for them to do,
but, yeah.
GLASS: Barry Mendel,
is he...
FILLLON: Summer Glau.
WHEDON: Not yet.
Some girl's foot.
BALDWIN: Barry Mendel is in an
American Express ad I saw recently.
WHEDON: Yes,
with Wes Anderson.
(CLAPPING)
FILLLON: Hey, Joss Whedon.
WHEDON: Yeah, hello.
Or, hey...
BALDWIN: Yeah, that's the thing
about the titles and the credits there.
My name comes over Nathan's
face. Jose's comes over your face...
I think we did it
alphabetically.
I mean, we weren't gonna do it as
everybody appeared because Morena doesn't,
Ron doesn't, you know.
BALDWIN: I would've liked It If
my name came on when I came on.
Yeah, yeah.
I bet you would've.
I was disappointed
that it was over his face.
Um, well, you know,
we were trying to throw off the audience,
because we felt they
weren't disoriented enough.
And then mine came over his face,
too. I mean, t thought that was, you know...
WHEDON: Hey, look,
it's the showroom from The 40 Year Old Virgin.
FILLLON: Yeah, it's true.
BALDWIN: This was a pickup, right?
This was a re-shoot.
WHEDON: Yeah,
that was a re-shoot. Uh-huh. This was,
middle of the movie,
let River give the movie to Mai.
The structure is basically
taken from Johnny Guitar, really.
Sterling Hayden.
You're Sterling Hayden.
And, Nathan,
you're Joan Crawford.
That's how it works. Yeah.
FILLLON: Joan Crawford?
I can do that.
Now, this mule was a lot of fun.
Baldwin: I remember we did our first
rehearsals out in the parking lot on this thing.
Like, "Okay, watch it!" And we found
out where all the sharp edges were.
Could they have made it
less user friendly?
WHEDON: Oh,
my God! It really was a razorblade with seats.
FILLLON: I've got a... Actually I've got
a picture on my MySpace page of me
taking a picture of myself
with the mule behind me.
And there's Adam poking his head up,
giving the finger behind my...
WHEDON: Not surprisingly.
The lovely Gina Torres.
Ah, forget about it, yes.
Huge applause.
Gina Torres is...
BALDWIN: That was a cool setup,
the way you tracked that.
Uh-huh. FILLLON: It's
like a little carnival ride.
Totally. I could completely see
that being the new Mummy ride
at Universal,
if you're listening...
(GLAU LAUGHING) WHEDON: Oh,
don't think it didn't cross my mind.
And, you know, if we...
Oh, wait,
here she comes. This is where I always lose it.
And I'm sad, now.
BALDWIN:
She looks good smudged.
You know, my dream,
if this had been...
if this had blown up huge, that the
mute ride was gonna be the biggest thing.
We all have dreams.
BALDWIN: It was like the two
weeks we did on location were
probably my favorite two
weeks working in... I don't know.
So,
pretty much... ”Cause they were up front,
the rest of the time,
just downhill.
Just miserable, just sad.
No, I'm just saying,
we all knew how much
pressure we were under,
we had to get it done
in that little window,
and then we get to the studio
where we had a little more control.
Yeah. And when the weather
cooperated and it was just...
It was just great.
FILLLON: I believe this was
our first day in the studio.
WHEDON:
Wait a minute, really?
Yeah, we finished our
two weeks out in the open
and we came back in
and we started filming this.
I do not remember that.
I'm pretty sure that's how...
I don't disagree.
I know we didn't go to the ship first,
'cause they hadn't finished building it.
I was also very excited because this
was the point... The outside stuff, anyway,
was the point where... That was the
first time I ever laid eyes on a Reaver.
Oh, yeah.
I was eating lunch across
from a couple of them.
Little off-putting.
Yeah.
Yeah, they really were.
Especially mouth guy.
I really liked mouth guy.
Yeah, that guy was
terrifying. And droopy-eye
guy. We featured him a lot.
Yeah.
BALDWIN: Did you wear shoes
in the show at all, Summer?
I had a pair of motorcycle boots
that I got to wear in some episodes.
Oh, that's right. In the fight,
you had the boots.
WHEDON: Yeah, we did put shoes on
her eventually, over my strong objections.
I think PETA had to go in and...
Or SAG, I guess it is, for...
I get those two confused.
(GLAU LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: Way to go, PETA.
Nice job, SAG!
FILLLON: Glenn.
WHEDON: Hey,
feet. Kids love feet. Glenn Howerton.
Yeah. Did a lovely job,
had to die.
Had to die, but...
GLASS: That's one of my
favorite moments in the Whole film.
WHEDON: I know.
Tell you what...
BALDWIN: That little
thing you do there.
FILLLON: Who knew Summer
could do comedy?
"GLASS: I love that moment.
WHEDON: It is. That little, "Of course, dummy.
"I'm perfectly cogent."
I love those.
I love throwing them in and, damn,
if that wasn't perfect on the first take.
And I love the first take,
'cause then you don't have a second one.
Oh, the Pepperidge Farm guy.
FILLLON: Some lovely voice work.
Dulcet tones.
Very beautiful. Very beautiful.
I believe professional opera singer,
this guy. Not sure.
Um, why did you...
You know,
it was a sound problem,
and I just threw it in,
literally, you know,
at Lisa Lassek's desk into
a microphone in the room,
and they never got a better one.
I mean, I don't
know if they tried.
They just let it slide.
So, you know,
I'm the Pepperidge Farm guy. I don't know why.
(ALL LAUGHING)
Every time my wife sees
that outfit she's like,
"You're a failure
as a filmmaker."
BALDWIN: We worked on this
machine-gun rig with the prop guy.
That is a capo from a parachute.
FILLLON: You loved it.
Oh, it was just great.
I remember
watching you practice,
and practice and practice... The prop
guy was so proud of the damn thing.
WHEDON: Well, he should've been.
It's a great moment. He made prop comedy.
You're a prop comic.
You're like Gallagher.
FILLLON: And what was this fellow's name,
the guard in the safe?
WHEDON: Oh, um...
(MUMBLING)
I remember hearing him
coming up to you saying...
Chuck! Sorry. Jesus.
I can't tell you? Yeah,
yeah, no, you can say it.
It was Chuck.
His name was Chuck.
I remember hearing him
coming up to you,
"What if the guard in the bank
is the same guy who runs out?"
And he's trying to, like, finagle
himself further and further into the movie.
Yes, he wanted to
be Glenn Howerton.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
GLAU: That's smart.
WHEDON: I know, it's like,
"And hello to you, too."
You know what? People
will always do it.
They'll always try and
get that little bit more.
(LAUGHING)
Hey, you know,
I did my little stint on Veronica Mars.
You think I wasn't pitching a romance
between the car rental guy and Veronica?
It's just in our blood.
What can we do?
BALDWIN: Now, this is where the stacks
of cash were that Nathan's been able to
pilfer and sign off on and hand
out as souvenirs to a lot of people.
Yeah, Universal
needs those back.
So, if you can track
down every fan...
BALDWIN: Yeah, Ion/y
grabbed a little stack.
FILLLON: I just told the prop guys
how much I appreciated that work
and I thought it looked cool, and they go,
"Here, take a couple stacks."
WHEDON: Now, do we want to talk about
the real reason you're shooting this guy?
FILLLON: Oh, yeah.
He used to date Morena.
And they went out for a time...
Which is why he had to die.
You were like,
"He gets on the ship,
"she's not gonna
look at me twice.
(ALL LAUGHING)
"I gotta get rid of him."
Yeah.
"Mule won't run with five."
Mule had five seats.
You are a liar, man.
BALDWIN: And we're
losing the seat.
FILLLON: That was like a last
minute thing you decided on,
the running into the stuff.
WHEDON: Yeah. Yeah,
we had a flat
and so we set up, you know...
FILLLON: "Let's smash it!"
...awnings and the fruit-cart kind of feel.
Now, this was a blast.
This was more fun than
any... WHEDON: This was fun.
...ride I'd been on.
More fun to shoot than to edit.
BALDWIN: And this stuff,
how complicated was that?
Loni...
WHEDON: This drove us crazy. These
were some of the last effects we finished.
Painting the bushes and stuff?
Yeah, had to paint in
bushes in a lot of places
and create the skiff behind them,
which to me...
You know, I would re-shoot
this in a heartbeat.
I feel like I made every
mistake a first-timer can make.
But I loved the shooting process, and I
love the fact that you guys were all there.
That we were trucking along.
And that, you know, Adam,
you were really hanging from that thing.
BALDWIN:
On wires, I love wires.
'Cause Nathan,
not as much wire love.
Nathan doesn't love himself
a harness. FILLLON.“ No.
Not so much with the
harness and the space suits.
I'd never seen you
cranky before.
My body needs to be free.
(WHEDON CHUCKLING)
GLAU: I know.
We were stuck out there.
FILLLON: I know,
I'm like that close to saying, "No underwear."
We had to go to the bathroom
and we were strapped into that thing.
WHEDON: That was... Yeah,
that was purely because it made the crew laugh.
We weren't even shooting.
We just drove back and forth,
and laughed and laughed.
(GUNS FIRING)
(SCREAMING)
Now, they actually got
an amputee stand-in there,
stuntman, to take the hit,
so that you could see the body
and not just do an insert of the leg.
They put a fake bottom of a leg
on him and I think...
I don't know if that came from
Chad or David Lester, the producer.
One of the guys came up with
that. BALDWIN: Chad, yeah.
Yeah, I think it was Chad.
It really helped the image...
GLAU: Looks awesome.
BALDWIN: This one particular day was,
I think, my favorite day.
WHEDON: This was great stuff. That one day,
hanging on the wire.
This shot is a Loni shot.
It was hot and nasty
and... Loved it.
That flyover Loni got
after the fact.
After we all left, when they did two
more days of just, you know, getting pieces.
Yeah, it was practical.
You know, it was
a silhouetted sequence and
framed so you couldn't see the arms.
They just rode it right over camera,
which is really cool.
Those rocks, give them a taste.
"Those CGI rocks!
Hit them."
BALDWIN: That papier-mâché
ought to stop them.
Hey, it did. Okay?
That was... That added foreground
was something that we, you know...
FILLLON: Actually,
you know, this bit I love.
This really nice, big,
beautiful dramatic build in the music
and then when the crash kind of happens,
it kind of winds down like a...
(IMITATES TAPE SLOWING DOWN)
WHEDON: We actually...
At the moment of the crash,
when we were in the mixing stage,
we had the orchestra.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING) GLAU:
Choreography. That is awesome.
BALDWIN: I love that little spindle move.
WHEDON: I know.
We had the Lazy Susan
just for that.
Yeah. That was
like our fifth mule.
Oh, it's so key.
But, yeah, right here,
the music...
It's... It's covered with
lots of smashing and stuff.
I made David Newman,
and it kind of appalled him,
but I asked him to have
the orchestra just go...
(IMITATES SCREECHING SOUND)
Just, like, lose it completely.
Just like, all the trumpets,
everybody, just to flare out.
Just like they had just
forgotten how to play their things
and went... Like, had a spasm,
and he did not like doing that,
because, you know,
he's a classical guy.
But you know, it's barely audible,
but I think it just fit the moment.
I didn't give David Newman nearly enough
props when I was doing my commentary
on this before because I was so...
'Cause I didn't have the sound on.
You know, 'cause, uh...
FILLLON: He did a lovely job.
I wasn't listening.
The music he created,
the opening, the themes.
Your theme,
where he found an old piano slightly out
of tune and he wrote River's theme on it.
'Cause he was like,
"I think this is River."
"This who she is,
this piano."
And I was like, "Oh, my God, you understand
this better than I do. You're so cool."
Did an amazing job.
Set course for Beaumonde.
First thing, I want this body...
KAYLEE: Simon!
(SPEAKING CHINESE)
FILLLON: Finally,
he gets a lick in.
BALDWIN: Finally,
he gets to speak Chinese. What're you saying?
(SPEAKING CHINESE)
Son of a whore or something,
I think I called him.
WHEDON: Probably, I mean,
it's something long.
SIMON: Never again.
Do you understand me?
FILLLON:
Yeah, I can't remember.
WHEDON: We haven't had too many complaints
about the Chinese, so it must've been...
FILLLON: You know,
I see all this stuff and it's so familiar to me.
Like, that cargo bay
is homey to me.
I see that,
I get a warm feeling,
rather than an industrial,
cold, kind of metal feeling.
WHEDON: Well, it's... You know,
the problem is it's working at cross purposes.
It's both.
First of all,
it's bluer than the one from the TV show.
But in the TV show, it was often
the gathering place
that had a homey feel.
And here, it's a
place of conflict.
More than that, it is
a little bluer because...
Because it isn't quite as homey,
because we didn't really
have time to have that,
get that homey feel.
We're kind of spending the
whole movie working towards,
"This is our home."
Um, so you're wrong.
All wrong.
You should play those
scenes again.
FILLLON: Never
contradict me.
(WHISPERING)
I'm sorry. Right.
And this was another
pickup shot.
Not this bit here, but...
Yeah.
I know. That was
a piece of mercy.
This...
Yeah, the close-up.
And Why did you... What
were you trying to establish?
Just be clearer. You know,
I get so flowery with the dialogue sometimes,
that some of the exposition...
Some of it I hide, I think, we“.
I'm not trying to put
myself down constantly.
And some of it I hide
in incomprehensible
flowery dialogue
that nobody understands
what's going on.
So we had to make very clear they
had to deliver to Fanty and Mingo,
they're running out of food,
they're living, literally, on the edge.
And have them go
into deep space.
Yeah, there is the pickup.
Yeah.
While he's saying it, so... it was,
you know, Mary... No.
I used the word "invaluable"
I think,
four times in my commentary. I listened to it
so I wouldn't repeat it,
and I've used it about
Mary, I think, twice.
Didn't use it about any
of you guys, it's weird.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING) I guess
you're all valuable and not invaluable.
FILLLON.“ Right.
WHEDON: Whew, good save.
I think the greatest
thing about having Gina
during the series was always,
I could kill you
and know that
I'd have a captain.
FILLLON: But you wouldn't,
right? Possibly a captain.
What? But you
wouldn't have done that.
Oh, yeah,
yeah. That was gonna be episode, like, 18.
But we never got there,
so you got to star in a movie.
BALDWIN: Wait,
don't you remember?
He was always giving us
these little subtle threats.
"You know, the show's
not called 'Mal'."
not called 'Jayne'."
Did you just say that
I did something subtle?
(ALL LAUGHING)
Subtlety is for little men.
Let's just look at those arms. Come on,
people.
FILLLON: Yeah,
holy pipes, man.
BALDWIN: We put oil on them to shine
them up a little bit. WHEDON: Uh, yeah!
FILLLON: You were dipped
in Vaseline every day.
WHEDON: Guess we
put him in the vat.
BALDWIN: "Makeup girls,
where's my oil?"
FILLLON: And we found it was easier
if we just wrapped him in Saran at night
so we wouldn't have to
re-dip him the next day.
BALDWIN: I got gamy.
I definitely got gamy.
WHEDON: How was that for Ami?
When you were gamy?
She doesn't mind.
...reached the edge of space,
saw a vasty nothingness...
GLASS: I love her.
WHEDON: There's Jewel.
I love this,
that this felt and then you kicked it,
and we happened to have both
cameras going so we got it for that shot.
GLAU: That's awesome.
That made me so happy.
Again, texture,
it's like cooking. BALDWIN: I had a pimple,
on my neck.
Oh, my God. That thing tasted,
like, a month.
But people probably can't see it on
the DVD and now you've pointed at it.
And you're supposed to point up there,
pimple on his...
See, there it is.
Here it comes.
But I don't think it's
in the next scene.
I think it goes away
in the next scene, 30...
Well, you know, we had the whole
scene where you have those wipes,
you know, those acne wipes.
But the film was just long.
You were like, "How can I
win Inara with this acne?"
And then you're wiping
your face crying.
FILLLON: Summer,
What are you doing?
(ALL LAUGHING)
What Joss told me to do.
WHEDON: Another one
of my unseemly jokes.
BALDWIN: What
is that smell?
FILLLON: Gotta get in there with
some luminol and a black light.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
- (IMITATING STEWIE) Yes, mmmh.
- FILLION: STEWIE.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
GLAU: That was
on my birthday.
WHEDON: That was? Wait,
the flashback? Yeah. Uh-huh.
FILLLON: That was
your birthday? Uh-huh.
Which birthday? How old did you turn?
WHEDON: So, you turned 15?
(GLAU LAUGHING)
I can't remember now.
But I got a cake. FILLLON: These
guys were good. Some good work.
WHEDON: I got a carrot
cake on my birthday.
That was when you guys
were in the shaft,
in the vent shaft,
and with Chuck in the...
GLAU: Oh, wow. Yeah.
BALDWIN: Yeah,
there was some big... WHEDON: The hat.
Sorry, but the hat. BALDWIN: I got
the hat. That was my homage to the hat.
Had to have the hat in there.
Sorry, what were you gonna say?
And I was gonna say,
in this little
sequence here,
there are some extras
who were big fans of the show,
and I think they got...
I don't know, they drew a lottery
or they just went in and auditioned,
cast in the movie. Boom.
WHEDON: Yeah.
FILLLON:
Someone won a contest?
Someone won
a contest. And...
She stood in one of
the publicity...
We took publicity stills 'cause
they had the cargo bay lit up.
And she stood in one of
them with us and it...
They put it on the cover of a book,
the novelization.
(ALL LAUGHING)
Advertisements by mistake.
And everyone saw it on Amazon.
Like, "Pre-order this book,"
and there's this woman and everyone's like,
"Uh, what?
We don't remember that."
FILLLON: She must
have loved it. Yeah.
Eventually, they changed it before
they actually put the book out. But, yeah...
I fear it isn't safe anymore.
Ah, hair placement.
FILLLON: Yeah, she always does...
You should comment about that.
WHEDON: Honorary member
of the 007-06,
the hair and makeup, because I was
so specific about Summer's hair. Just...
I mean, there were cut scenes
that were just hair and feet.
Remember? When you're
unlocking yourself from... GLAU: Yes.
Yeah? Doing all that...
I worked hard at that.
That had your hair
and your feet.
I was like... FILLLON: This
was Alan's birthday. This day.
And his last day.
What?
His last day on the show
was this one.
Really?
Yeah.
BALDWIN: Isn't this when you
put up all the pictures?
WHEDON: This is... Yes...
FILLLON: Part of, you know...
WHEDON: Our thing was, you know,
Alan's schedule was always...
Part of the reason he's not here,
he's appearing on Broadway.
Or as we call it in show business,
The Broadway.
GLASS: Show-off.
He's always working.
Although not as much
as Chiwetel Ejiofor.
Four movies in this year alone.
Kinky Boots, Four Brothers,
and Melinda and Melinda, same year as this.
And then, since then,
he's gone on to appear in every film made
(GLASS LAUGHING)
in the world ever.
FILLLON: Including porn.
And some porn.
And I just saw him on stage in
London in The Seagull. It was amazing.
It was really cool.
We hung out and he
wanted me to tell you
that he...
Nathan is a bad brain
and that when he would hit Nathan,
he would... It'd feel good to hit Nathan.
I think those were
his exact words.
GLASS: How did you tell the
difference between Yan and Rafael?
I never,
ever knew the difference between Yan and Rafael.
Rafael has a little mole.
And I admitted it freely.
Yes, I know.
He has a thing in is eye, little dot in
his eye. FILLLON: A dot on his eye.
The problem was,
I knew one of them had a dot in his eye,
(ALL LAUGHING) but I
forgot which one it was!
They told me, but I just...
I couldn't do it.
Hey, this must be the
future, there's a thing,
a samovar that self-pours. I love
anything like that. GLAU: Cool!
But, yeah. No, I just
freely admit it.
Every morning I would come up,
"Hi, which one are you?"
Just don't let...
No games.
BALDWIN: Yeah, I'd have to go
right up close to their face and go,
"Ah, hi, Rafael."
He goes, "Ah, good..."
Yeah,
I did start to get it right towards the end,
I think.
But I can't tell now.
But now it's tough. Yeah.
GLAU: So which one has the
mole? BALDWIN: That's Nathan.
WHEDON: Which twin
has the Tony?
You're sure that's Nathan?
That's Nathan.
FILLLON: The lighting
was so bad in this...
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: Drunk and insane.
My muscular buttocks it's 40.
It is,
as of now.
FILLLON: Here's comes trouble.
GLAU: I'm wearing my shoes.
WHEDON: Yeah,
I know. What's that about? I'm ready to fight.
Oh, right. Oh, right.
FILLLON: There's a pretty good
scene gearing up right here,
but someone's gotta
come in there.
(GLAU GIGGLES) How
long were you in fight camp?
WHEDON: You guys had
a beautiful dialogue scene,
and she just, literally,
walked over it.
(GLAU GIGGLES)
FILLLON: Summer, how long
were you in fight camp?
Or fight-like-a-girl camp?
WHEDON: The first rule of fight camp,
(GLAU GIGGLES) we do not
talk about fight camp. No, go ahead.
GLAU: Three months.
FILLLON: Three months?
Felt like three years.
WHEDON: I thought it was more.
I thought you were...
Well, I started
six months before.
You started training
six months before. Yeah.
But fight camp,
which Nathan showed up to
for an hour sometimes...
FILLLON: I would show up and she'd
be working her ass off. I'd do a little bit...
(FILLLON GIBBERING)
By the time I left, she was doing so
much by then. I was like, "See you later."
BALDWIN: Remember the day
that... Was it Buchanan that brought
the Fruity Oaty Bars song?
FILLLON: Yes, Buchanan.
The day that came
on the set we just,
"Play it again.
Play it again."
WHEDON: It's going through
my head for most of the shoot.
The guys who wrote it,
we didn't change a thing.
We changed some of the visuals but,
yeah, that song... FILLLON.“ Love this bit.
Now, this scene was
actually improv. So...
(ALL LAUGHING)
It turned out, a lot of
those guys have rage
they just haven't dealt with.
FILLLON: Summer, What are you
thinking about when you're watching this?
Just thinking about how
many times I worked on it.
Are you proud?
Once.
I could've done it better but...
BALDWIN: Chad Stahelski.
WHEDON: Yeah, and Him.
Hiro does the great
back-crunching fall
that comes later.
BALDWIN: I love that move.
Yes, yes. And this one.
Boom. There we go.
I watched this,
you know, 'cause, you know,
we edited the movie for, like, four years.
It was like Apocalypse Now.
FILLLON: Here goes Hiro.
Every time this scene grew...
That's the one, that's Hiro.
Every time this scene came on,
we played it through to the end.
We never, ever skipped
over it. Ever.
FILLLON: Yeah. In, like,
literally, 13 months of editing.
It was just... It was just
the most fun you could have.
Love that kick.
There's a little
bit of doubling.
Just the twirling.
BALDWIN: I love these.
They just crunch him.
WHEDON: I know. Jayne's
attitude is... They just put him down.
Why are you like this?
BALDWIN: This whole thing... She
wouldn't grab my nuts, she wouldn't do it.
I said, "Come on."
Harder.
WHEDON: That's...
There's absolutely
no sensation there.
(ALL LAUGHING)
Harder.
WHEDON: She was trying
not to hurt him.
GLAU: You told me
to go for it.
And then, here's a great look. Both
actors hiding their faces perfectly
(GLAU LAUGHS) while all doing
their own stunts. Thank you, guys.
GLAU: And he was good.
See, what this basically is,
is we don't have a lot of money.
We have a ballerina. It's
like a great special effect.
Instead of, you know,
being in slow motion over a guy
and adding a lot of digital effects,
we can just have Summer
work really hard for nine months
and use that instead.
FILLLON: One pull of that trigger,
it all could have been over.
(BALDWIN SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
(WHEDON REPEATING RUSSIAN)
WHEDON: "This is
laughter for chickens."
it means, "This is absurd," or it did way
back when, when my old Russian teacher
in high school, Count Salahab,
taught it to me.
(BALDWIN REPEATING IN RUSSIAN)
WHEDON: He was actually...
He was such an elderly fellow.
He was... His father fought
against the Russian Revolution.
FILLLON: Oh, my God.
Was in fact, a count.
And he was smuggled
out of Russia,
a fascinating man.
Taught me that phrase,
and I always thought
if! had a...
If! ever wrote an autobiography,
which, of course,
at the age of 17,
I was thinking,
um, because I'm so fun of me,
that I would call it,
Laughter For Chickens.
Because I thought that the
absurdity of it just embodied everything,
and so I threw it in.
I figured it couldn't be Chinese because
somebody might accidentally say it
if it was Chinese. It should
be something you didn't...
You weren't used to hearing.
FILLLON: Now here. "Captain."
It said "Captain,"
when really in the Army,
I was a sergeant, and I've
read this on the Internet.
Was that a mistake?
No, no. That was
an intricate thing.
I'll tell you about it later.
FILLLON: 'Cause it's... The
record had been updated.
Did it say "Captain of
Serenity" or did it say...
BALDWIN: Was he promoted
in the field?
FILLLON: I'm sorry,
it just said "Captain."
BALDWIN:
Promoted in the field.
WHEDON: No, probably, if we put
any thought... I mean, we put so much...
You know, that used to be
a big exposition scene,
followed by another
exposition scene,
and then later on,
I thought I'd try some exposition...
FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
...to go with my exposition.
Tra-la!
I know how to write.
But, um...
BALDWIN: Wait, we skipped over
the frozen grapes I had in that bag
that I was using to cool
my goolies. They're coming.
They're coming. Frozen
grapes are coming.
They're coming. They'll
make an appearance.
FILLLON: You holding
them right now?
But, um...
If we put Sergeant and then Captain,
there's so much information.
FILLLON: People confused.
Yeah.
We had to cut down
on the information.
All right.
But not on the frozen grapes
held to your... To Adam's nuts.
If I speak the words...
FILLLON: Grape nuts. BALDWIN:
Which was Nathan's idea in rehearsal.
He came up with, "Hey, why don't you have some,
like, frozen grapes there?"
And I was like, "Yeah, that'd be good.
I can eat them as I'm doing the scene."
(BALDWIN CHOMPING)
They were crunchy.
WHEDON: Of course.
But that got cut out because you got
these two guys bitching at each other.
You know, throwing down.
WHEDON: Well, no, the
grapes are in there.
You use them, you hold
them, you eat them.
My God, what do you... Should
they have had a musical number?
Didn't you say earlier,
you like the cooking and the eating...
Yeah,
there's eating. You're gonna see yourself eat.
MAL: My crew!
Just see you in a minute.
You had a gorramn
time bomb living with us!
WHEDON: Some of the...
Uh-oh.
Shooting below... BALDWIN:
She gets all the good shots.
Not none of them. I'm not
gonna He. She gets some of them.
FILLLON: See that chair, Ron, that empty
one? That's Where you would have been.
(MEN LAUGHING)
GLASS: I am there.
WHEDON: Oh, well, you know,
we can digitally line it up.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
And you can just shake
your head disapprovingly.
There, okay, grapes!
BALDWIN: You can't
tell that's a grape.
What is it? Look, yeah,
there's a grape.
And...
(SOFTLY) Eat the grape, eat the grape,
eat the grape, eat the grape.
It's important that we're really dealing
with the intricacies of filmmaking.
BALDWIN: I know. I wanted it to
be a scene about frozen grapes.
And you had this other idea.
Again, you know... After,
you know... Once you've done any,
even tiny amount of acting...
Oh, eating a grape.
Focus, focus.
Yeah, but you're eating.
You can tell.
Can I make a suggestion
that doesn't involve violence...
Once you've done a tiny bit of acting,
even in your living room,
you do realize that it is
all about the grapes.
Like, you know,
it's all about the spear you're holding.
GLASS: I remember,
I didn't... This is where I stopped watching.
After this...
Before this scene.
WHEDON: Wait. Really?
You actually stopped?
No. No.
You got bored?
No.
(WHEDON SIGHS)
I'm a little sad.
FILLLON: David Krumholtz.
You could not find a Mr. Universe.
WHEDON: Not for a while.
Not for a While.
I thought that I had made a terrible
mistake by writing the part of Mr. Universe.
People just weren't getting it.
It sounded terrible.
It sounded like I don't know how to write,
which is what you think...
When you hear someone read
your stuff badly you...
Sometimes you think, "Okay,
that guy's not getting it."
But usually you think,
"I just don't know how to write."
And then you hear somebody
who can really act,
and you think,
"I'm a great writer."
it's weird,
but they don't come into the equation that much.
It's, you know,
it's all about my grapes. FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
(BALDWIN LAUGHS)
FILLLON: Nectar Rose,
I see her up on my hike all the time.
WHEDON: Really? Yeah. "Hi, Nectar,
I'll probably see you tomorrow."
(GLAU CHUCKLES)
MAL: Well, what
about this?
WHEDON: Nectar, the world champion...
GLASS: How often do you hike?
WHEDON:
...standing-still person.
FILLLON: When I'm
unemployed or right now?
You can do that?
Once a week now
that I'm working,
but, like, five times a
week if I'm unemployed.
WHEDON: NOW, is this,
like, hiking?
'Cause you... I...
You're in shape.
FILLLON: There's an easy one and
there's a little bit more difficult ones.
GLAU: The one with the
stairs is really hard.
That's a tough one,
that's the one I like.
BALDWIN: That's a
good sweaty hike.
WHEDON: Um, I...
I've heard of exercise,
and it sounds,
quite frankly, dangerous.
And a little unseemly,
unchristian.
Lenore wrote her own vows...
And here's something else.
GLASS: (LAUGHING)
I love... I love...
I love the marriage. David was
a little... He was like, you know...
"I kind of liked the fact that I
wasn't being cast as Jewish."
"You know, that I was just being cast as this,
sort of weird guy."
"I was like, " But the
texture, you know,
"the culture that you
bring with yourself
"is so important. It's all these
people have. " FILLLON.“ Yeah.
He lives on this desolate moon with you know,
a robot.
It's like, you gotta have this,
you gotta have this moment of heritage,
'cause that's kind of exactly
what the show and the movie is.
And then he was, like,
cool with it but...
And I got what he was saying. He did
just sort of wanna be this free-floating guy.
But, at the same time, those little moments,
they just make it so human.
FILLLON: Agreed.
Subliminal.
All of that stuff had to be shot around
the fact that when I got to the monitors,
they couldn't work two
of them at the same time.
They couldn't, like,
have two of them going,
so I kept, like, panning up and
tilting and move... Roving the camera
from monitor to monitor because
they literally couldn't work them
at the same time, you know.
The mother of invention is
that somebody else messed up.
And that was the last day,
I think. 80 my patience was...
They're afraid of me.
FILLLON: I love these bits between Sean
and Summer. Oh, don't get me started.
I've already ranted about this.
80, Summer, What was it like?
This was probably
my hardest day.
This or the day on Miranda.
And this came second?
This was one of our first
days on the ship. Yes. It was.
Old men covered in blood.
FILLLON: This was difficult
for you because it's emotional?
Yeah. It was hard.
WHEDON: You know, Sean is
constantly making faces, throwing her off.
I mean, he's so unprofessional.
FILLLON: That is his face.
(GLAU LAUGHS)
WHEDON: (LAUGHING)
He's making it now.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
FILLLON: He can't help that.
GLASS: This is coming up on
another one of my favorite moments, too.
Miranda.
WHEDON: But this was,
you know... What was this, like, two takes?
GLAU: We did it all day.
No,
we didn't. We didn't? It felt like all day.
No, because Jack lit you both at the same time,
first of all, which was great.
But, really, you got this thing in,
like, two or three takes.
Am I talking to Miranda now?
Uh, maybe four.
FILLLON: There's the look.
Yes, the look.
There was a line after it,
and it was so clearly
unnecessary. FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
"It was like, " No,
"that's doing the work."
...it somehow
brought this up.
FILLLON: I love that there's
blood on her but none of it's hers.
Yes.
The memory, it isn't mine.
WHEDON: I was always very... You know,
I had the PG-13 to protect.
And I didn't know how much
I could get away with.
How much blood and
actually, you know,
we had to go back, like,
three times to get the PG-13,
'cause of
the Reavers' faces and...
You know, Mal just shoots
a lot of guys for...
Who aren't shooting at him,
and I don't know.
I don't know what
it was exactly.
But it was tough. It was
tough to get the PG-13.
BALDWIN: (IMITATING GLAU)
"Bullet in the brainpan, squish!"
Things are going to
get much, much worse.
WHEDON: We could just
do the dialogue.
FILLLON.“ I'll do it.
Boy, let's talk about
how cool Mal is.
(BALDWIN CHUCKLES)
That's one of my
favorite relationships.
WHEDON: (IMITATING CHIWETEL)
"I've come to talk"
"to you about the coolness
of Mal. He's cooler than I am."
Hmm.
Ah, the waterfall that caused
an entire scene to be unfilmable
because of sound
and then was used
for exactly that length of time.
FILLLON: Ladies and gentlemen,
Mr. Ron Glass.
Yeah,
yeah. You totally... That was a spoiler.
Because we haven't seen him yet.
Oh, right.
I love this shot, actually.
There we go.
(CLAPPING) Ladies and gentlemen,
Mr. Ron Glass!
The film begins.
FILLLON:
Looking good, big guy.
GLAU: Yeah, looking good.
WHEDON: And then back
to one of the first.
BALDWIN: Then I had this Whole
little bit worked out With the cigars, and...
I know, we talked
about the cigars
and we had a scene that we shot
where Ron gave you the cigars...
BALDWIN: Oh, and how crappy
a guitar player am I?
You are not Edward Van Halen.
But I gave you that thing to learn,
like, the morning before.
And then they were, like,
"You know, you can't..."
"You can't really use
it anyway, so we..."
So David wrote something. You did fine,
you were great.
FILLLON: Ron, you were
about to say something.
I was just thinking about
the fact that I got my niece
to braid my hair.
Is that who braided your hair?
Yeah? Huh? Yeah.
And I had to...
And I did it, like,
four, five days before we actually
shot so that I could muss it a little bit.
And then when it was over,
that night, I went home
and I just cut it off
with scissors myself.
The braids?
Uh-huh.
I love this scene, though.
WHEDON: This was the scene... First of all,
I think it's one of the most beautiful.
And second of all,
I just love the play between you guys.
And you know, there is
a moment, by the way,
where I'm holding on
the back of your head
for an extra moment
while he's speaking.
And Lisa, the editor, was like,
"Are you really gonna hold
on the back of his head?"
"I'm like, " There is no way
"I'm not putting those
braids in this movie."
Because you couldn't really
see them in the other shots.
And I was like...
They were so gorgeous.
And when Jack had them side-lit,
the way they all came down.
Oh, it was just so pretty, I was like, "Yes,
we have to. These braids are important."
They're like Summer's feet.
FILLLON: I was Whipping
the rocks at Adam there.
BALDWIN: "Adam, stop playing
that guitar down there."
(WHISPERING)
I was just touching it.
It was like a Greek theater.
WHEDON: Yeah,
I had you playing into the Wide shots.
GLASS: Why do you
always think that?
Why do you always think
I'm talking about God?
FILLLON: So pretty up there.
That's also Where we filmed...
WHEDON: How do you feel
about that line?
The Train Job was up there.
Yeah.
GLASS: I love that line.
I love that line.
Oh, good.
Because it always...
'Cause I was talking about him,
and he always, you know...
People always think that
they're talking about something
outside of themselves,
always. You know, rather than...
Especially if you're a preacher.
Yeah.
A shepherd.
(GLASS LAUGHS)
Yeah, it...
Well, I mean...
It's funny 'cause we did
all those press junkets.
They'd ask me what the movie's about. I'd take,
like,
45 minutes to try and explain it,
which is not a sound bite.
And so I need to
learn that skill.
And I could've
just said, "Belief."
FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
I mean, that really is...
It's just, if you believe in something,
you have an anchor.
And if you don't,
and it doesn't matter what it is,
but if you have something...
'Cause it's,
you know... This whole process is basically
Mal getting something.
(GLASS GIBBERING)
Whoa,
everybody gets something in this scene.
FILLLON: Hello, handsome.
(WHEDON CHUCKLING)
WHEDON: Had the root
beer and... Was it a jelly donut?
FILLLON: It was Dr. Pepper
and it was a chocolate donut.
See, you can't let me tell stories,
I don't know anything.
Dr. Pepper and a chocolate
donut sitting on the monitor.
When I said, "Okay,
scene is wrapped."
(ALL LAUGHING)
Chocolate donut in one bite.
He had been waiting for
his shirtless scene to be over.
And then, of course, you know...
BALDWIN: I kept getting the,
"Did you get those diuretics yet?"
"Did you get those
supplements yet?"
(WHEDON LAUGHING)
"Working hard on that diet,
right? Shirt off scene coming up."
"Shirt off scene
coming up, huh?"
It worked.
FILLLON: Yeah.
Yeah, you got motivated. WHEDON:
You look good. You look good.
I should've shot more
with your shirt off.
I think, actually,
that just goes for the whole crew.
That would've been a DVD extra.
FILLLON: This was a good scene.
Yes, it was.
Talk about it.
I actually played this scene
with a pre-recorded Morena.
BALDWIN: But you also played the
scene with Morena when she pre-recorded it.
Right. So I just kind of sat in the room
with Morena while she filmed that scene
and we played out this nice little scene,
trying not to overlap each other.
But then I came and just
played it with the recording,
like, a week later.
WHEDON: And she... Her performance,
it's like she was phoning it in.
It was exactly the same.
(GLAU GIGGLING)
Honestly.
That was fun. it was fun to play with that,
play with your pauses
and the two of you
not being able to
express anything,
as should be the case
in any romantic comedy,
which for short periods of time,
this film is.
FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
Love this bit, too.
Inara, nice to see her again.
WHEDON: I still think that shot
bringing you in is really awkward.
BALDWIN: I like how your
voice goes into falsetto here.
Oh, that's the outtake.
Never mind.
Yeah, but,
remember the part where it's a trap?
WHEDON: We're gonna talk
about his problem,
Nathan finally hitting puberty.
FILLLON: What?
(WHISPERING) Boys' problems.
Nothing. It's good.
Just, we're loving you.
(CLEARS THROAT)
(FILLLON SIGHS)
I love this movie.
I'm referring here to people.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay.
Wait a minute.
Was it this?
BALDWIN: Is the red button
on the bridge here?
Did Alan bring
the red button in?
The red button is still
in my office at home.
But it didn't make it into this?
It didn't make it into the set.
It's one of those things that
t left. We got the dinosaurs.
We got the dinosaurs.
But then we had to take out part
of Nathan looking at the dinosaurs.
We had that long,
coming all the way around you.
You know, in the long out. We had
to cut into it. FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
I was sad because you took a
moment to look at the dinosaur.
Yeah, I took a moment to kind of
re-adjust to the picture he was setting.
Well, that moment
fell by the wayside
so that we could come
in under two hours.
Which, damn it,
I'm still proud of. Right.
I wanna live there.
FILLLON: This was
another great day.
This was a day I was very much
looking forward to. We worked really hard.
Not as hard as Summer,
but very hard.
Yeah, she actually went
to sleepover fight camp.
You just had day camp.
Right.
Mal! What are
you doing here?
And dignity, always dignity.
Well, that makes you kind of a tease,
doesn't it?
You knew my invitation
wasn't on the level.
BALDWIN: Our Mrs. Reynolds.
I'm fine. I'm giddy.
WHEDON: I could watch
you two argue for a long while.
It's one of my great pleasures,
is watching you and Morena
go back and forth.
FILLION: I think it's one of Mel's
great pleasures to argue with Inara.
It's a good point.
I think so.
It's just the...
All of the juice between them,
it comes out in arguments.
Those are their love scenes,
and they are so much fun.
...in that outfit.
FILLLON: I love these two guys,
measuring each other up,
taking a look at each other,
and then,
Mal so cleanly,
so clearly... Excuse me.
But I mean it when I say...
Uh, cannot take this guy.
No.
Clearly outmatched.
WHEDON: Oh, I thought you
meant couldn't take him as a person.
But yeah, no,
he is. He's completely outmatched in a fight.
It's worse than you know.
It usually is.
And it's... You know,
one likes to think that the plucky hero
who's all heart
would win the day.
But Mal would've had his
head cut off if it wasn't for Inara.
Way I remember it,
albatross was a
ship's good luck...
FILLLON: One of my
favorite lines in the movie.
Which?
The poem. "We read a
poem. Try not to faint."
You know, I wondered
if it was too broad.
No, I love that and
the other little bit,
"Oh, please, give him
an hour." I love it.
I loved reading it,
loved doing it.
That was fun. It's always
fun to have the moment of,
"Yeah... Hey!"
It's the...
I love moments.
Little... You are so
amazing about moments.
I just love the fact
that that is the...
You know,
that the albatross was the ship's good luck
and now it's come
to me in something
that's a burden, but in fact,
it was something nice.
And that he uses that.
That's really...
It's nautical stuff.
It's like, "That's what
a captain would know."
That's the poem he would've read
if he's got a ship.
And I think of it as a boat
more than any other thing.
Most of the reference I have for it,
you know, I think of,
is submarine stuff,
is boat stuff.
It's not so much airplanes,
because that's not... BALDWIN: Airplanes.
You know, that's a guy
in a cockpit.
That's not the same kind of
community that a boat is.
FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
You know, my brother, Sam,
was first mate on a fishing boat in Alaska,
for years, every summer.
Salmon boat.
And I had him come talk to the
writers when we started the series
about, well, just stuff
he'd been through.
Because, you know, people just dead
in the water, ships sinking. I mean, just...
Completely life on the edge,
very much like this.
How long do you think
you can really run from us?
FILLLON: It's terrifying.
Yeah.
He had some incredible stories.
I should tell you,
so that you don't waste your time...
FILLLON: And this, too,
another moment that defines who Malcolm is.
Yeah. Loved reading it,
loved doing it.
Yeah, this was one of those,
when I figured it out I was like,
"Yeah, okay, this sells. This
is a thing that explains a lot."
(GUN FIRES)
Idiot.
Yeah,
I know. Should've gone for the face.
I am, of course,
wearing full body armor.
I am not a moron.
INARA: Wait, just let...
Not afraid to hit a girl.
No.
A lot.
BALDWIN: Rag doll.
She... He totally
rag-dons her. It's great.
WHEDON: I like this.
Anything, you know,
when the camera gets hit by accident
has that sweet little energy.
(GRUNTING)
That's you. We always held long enough
so people could see you were doing it.
FILLLON.“ Nice. BALDWIN.“
I love that little touch there.
You get some bumps and
bruises during this sequence?
Oh, once or twice.
But you know what?
I'd rather be bumped and
bruised than it look stupid.
WHEDON: Yeah.
There's... Where is there
I saw there was a miss?
Oh, it was just on a TV show,
but there was an obvious miss.
And it kills me. You know,
there's an obvious miss in The Godfather,
where James Caan clearly
does not hit a guy.
GLAU: Yes, I saw that.
Yeah. I was watching
it the other day.
BALDWIN: It's like seeing
the boom come in, right?
Yeah, it's just like,
it so takes me out of it,
'cause I believe this.
I believe all of this
is really happening.
FILLLON: I remember there's an
extra head butt in this fight that got cut.
Because, apparently,
England was having a problem with head butts.
England. Yes!
That's right. They have
a head butt law.
Too much head butting,
apparently.
Yeah.
So it became a problem. They
have completely different standards.
I mean, they can show full frontal
nudity on TV and say anything they want.
But, you know, you
can't see, you know,
Porky's if you're under 35.
I mean, it's a very weird
system. It's different.
He isn't the plucky hero.
In some ways, you know,
I guess it's true with all cultures.
In some ways, it's much more prurient
and in some ways, it's much more relaxed.
Oh, yeah.
(LAUGHS) We walked
right into that.
Rather conveniently, in fact.
Just a flash bomb.
Go. Go!
The indoor mountain set.
That's all we managed
to maintain.
What was that? Two days of
shooting at the indoor mountain set?
FILLLON: Yeah.
That's all we kept.
Ah,
here's... What'd he call them? Beer kegs.
Is that the only time we see
the firefly effect in the entire film?
No, we see it when you guys
run away from the Reavers.
And that shot was popped in
from a different scene.
Just so we could build...
BALDWIN: People in Beverly Hills
wear those things all the time now.
What? You see them walking
down the street in Beverly Hilts
with those little
earwigs on now.
Well,
this doesn't take place that far in the future.
It takes place in 2007,
which is, weirdly, now.
Why,
'cause this guy beat up Mal? That ain't so hard.
BALDWIN: Oh, here we are
in my big yellow shirt scene.
FILLLON: Adam,
if I remember correctly,
you had a hard time spitting
out one of your lines.
Yeah,
because I got confused with the blocking.
The blocking kept
screwing me up on that pivot.
It's just that...
No. The blocking was
to stay in the chair.
No, no. Later when I get up
and I get all, like, testy.
Stand up.
...on River's mind.
WHEDON: That's right,
you had to move one of your legs
(FILLLON CHUCKLING)
during a line and that was...
No, this isn't when I had trouble
here. 'Cause it's all on you guys.
WHEDON: No, I know.
I know.
FILLLON: There we are,
right there.
BALDWIN: No,
I remember this one.
I seem to remember you
getting really frustrated. Not yet.
WHEDON: See, that used to be... See,
that was where your...
Where your little bit that we
cut out was in. BALDWIN: Yeah.
FILLLON: This part made famous
by a television commercial.
WHEDON: That was
a scene transition.
We put those scenes together
where we cut to you upstairs.
No offense,
Doc. I think it's noble as a grape...
Now, the St. Christopher
medal around my neck
is the thing I stole off the guard I killed,
or I knocked out, in the...
You also stole his patch,
which you're patting
as you walked out of the cargo bay. Patch,
yes.
GLASS: Those shirts.
Were those shirts...
Were those shirts a gift from
somebody? WHEDON: Me.
That was my crew gift,
the yellow Jayne shirts.
FILLLON: Mine smell bad.
GLAU: I don't think
I got one!
WHEDON: I gave... I made them in all sizes,
in girl sizes, too.
Yeah, that...
You were a little timid there.
BALDWIN: I couldn't
get the rhythm right.
WHEDON: Of course,
then I realized that I have children
and I can't go around
wearing a big gun on my shirt,
which I didn't
really realize it had.
FILLLON: I actually remember looking
at this scene and talking to Jack Green
and saying, "I really love
the way you lit this."
Where, you know, we're talking
about two sides of Malcolm Reynolds,
and you got one side
kind of lit warm
and one side lit kind
of icy blue. And he said,
"Oh, yeah, look how
that worked out."
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: Well, that's Jack.
Yeah.
"Oh, did I make art?
"I'm sorry, I'll clean that up." “Hey,
that's kind of cool.“
I came looking for you.
To me, it's...
it's tough, because there's a fine line
when you light like that between, you know,
like 803 lighting, where you know,
you got that hot blue coming in.
And the fill is
the same as the key
and it can start to
look like a disco.
FILLLON: Yeah, yeah.
You got to walk the line.
River and I will
get off at Haven.
Well, you like discos.
Nobody besides Jayne
is saying that.
I don't know. I'm just
assuming that about you.
I got no answers for you,
Inara. I got no rudder.
This is another scene that came
and went in the editing, that I love.
And we had to re-shoot it.
Because the light... There was
something wrong with the tight.
The shutter, something went...
(SPLUTTERS)
The light was strobing or
something. We had to do it twice.
FILLLON: I don't even
remember that.
That's the trouble
with doing a commentary
eight years after
we did the movie.
WHEDON: Also,
counting to three years after, not eight.
Right.
Also, this scene
came before that.
We had a whole... We
had all this flippity stuff.
FILLLON: Was that the same
location Where we filmed...
Now, where was this location?
This was in Pasadena
at that garden at that big old, like,
library, or something like that.
I forget. It's some...
You can see all this
great old stuff there.
I remember because the producer
took me here once to look at some stuff
while we were trying to talk about story,
or t was trying to talk about story.
And it has, you know,
all these old manuscripts.
This effect doesn't quite
come off the way I'd hoped.
I don't really feel like I'm looking
from this world into that one.
But it sort of works.
It wasn't in the budget,
so we had to...
So we just sort of had
to get creative with it.
GLAU: I get it.
You do?
Yeah, it makes sense to me.
Okay.
That's mouth guy.
FILLLON: Yeah.
He's a fave.
I love that look. I love
that look on your face.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
Look at those... Oh,
she's angry. And then, of course...
Nice choice of...
Low and wide.
BALDWIN: I put real alcohol
in that, in that one take.
Did you?
Uh-huh.
What were you looking for,
besides a fine, fine buzz?
Smell.
Looking for the smell.
FILLLON: You had that
in spades, my friend.
(BEEPING)
No trouble, little crazy person.
WHEDON: I love shooting Jayne
because he lives in his hero world,
so I can use all those low angles
and, you know, arch camera moves,
because he's Jayne.
He's not living
in a documentary.
FILLLON: This was my
shortest day on Serenity.
I came in,
and I did this
about three times,
and I went home.
(CHUCKLES)
WHEDON: He's actually
getting in his car.
(ALL LAUGHING) He
directly left the set from there.
And I love this bit.
WHEDON: I never get
tired of doing that.
GLAU: I actually hit
Sean on one take.
Well, of course you did.
You've always hated Sean.
(GLAU CHUCKLES)
This wasn't even in the script.
They talked it out and she said,
"Let me try a thing this take."
BALDWIN: Lucky the
camera caught it.
She's sealed off the
bridge. I do not like her there.
I wish I could've kept
some of those guns.
They're really cool.
FILLLON: I did.
Did you?
I kept all your guns.
(WHISPERING) Can
I borrow them? No.
Oh. Please?
I love that.
WHEDON: I love that because it took us
a really long time to figure out how to cut
into you getting up because
it took a really long time
to get you out of that thing.
The editor found a nice way to
just slice in there while
you're putting it down.
FILLLON: All those things
that Firefly and Serenity
are famous for.
Being a...
You can see the
exposed lighting.
WHEDON: The flares.
On firefly, the lens package,
they had more of a circle.
They'd get this sort of
703 circle flare. Halo.
These would just pop
out a little bit.
BALDWIN: Is that gun
heavy, Summer?
GLAU: Yes, they had to help
prop it up for me on certain takes.
WHEDON: in the take where she clicks it,
it is, in fact, on a C-stand.
After Mal gets off. You see,
now, that for me,
with the face in darkness
instead of the blue light, that,
for me, it feels
more real, it feels...
I think that's as
beautiful as it gets.
FILLLON: Yes. I get prettier
the more of my face you hide.
(WHEDON LAUGHING)
Here we go.
There, that one's propped up.
GLAU: Yeah, it's too still. Yeah,
I know. That's tough.
FILLLON: It was heavy and it
was pointing behind your head.
It was shakier than Katharine
Hepburn's head on a helicopter.
(MEN LAUGHING)
Miranda.
WHEDON: Huh?
How can it be there's a
whole planet called Miranda
and none of us knowed that?
Because there isn't one.
FILLLON: I love these days.
WHEDON: And sunlight.
FILLLON: Everybody
on the bridge.
Ron, remember those days?
(ALL LAUGHING)
I didn't know if you were
going to make me sleep.
WHEDON: Good times. Good.
Lack of good times.
Some years back,
there was call for workers to settle on Miranda.
Daddy talked about it.
Nothing about it on the Cortex.
BALDWIN: I kept shifting
my hand back and forth.
Sometimes on the left,
sometimes on the right.
WHEDON: What?
FILLLON: Superstition?
Baldwin: Just did it on purpose.
Just to mess with continuity.
WHEDON: That's not funny.
Do you know how hard it is?
It was never funny.
I love moving with Gina there.
I love having the one shot.
That's something I read Scorsese said,
not that I, you know,
learned a damn thing,
but he said he has one or two shots that
he knows he needs and
the rest of it is negotiable.
That, for me,
everything in that works around getting Gina
to go over there and
bring us to that screen.
Just in this, like,
sort of electric fashion.
And everything else is just
shots of you guys. Whatever.
So that I get the B-camera
to pick that up.
Some fire, some corpses.
FILLLON: You see that
location on TV all the time.
I'll bet. I'll bet.
We were never allowed
to go out of the zone.
Except, I think,
for the funeral scene.
I think that was
out of the zone.
FILLLON: Is that like a certain
amount of distance you can travel?
Yeah. BALDWIN:
There's the little dead kid.
Yeah, he was alive
and then he's dead.
BALDWIN: Sort of established a
relationship with Kaylee earlier but...
I love that shot.
FILLLON:
Yeah, that's pretty.
FILLLON: Ladies and gentlemen,
Mr. Ron Glass.
WHEDON: There's some
big laughs in this scene.
Well, actually, everything that
comes out of your mouth is a joke.
FILLLON.“ Yeah, it's true.
You really take death
like a pro.
GLASS: I love
the homage to...
That Redford movie.
FILLLON: The mountain
man movie? Yeah.
Oh, uh, "Killed the ship
that killed us."
GLASS: "I killed the
bear that killed me."
Yeah.
WHEDON: I think of that
not so much as an homage,
as, "Wow, I totally
stole that by accident."
And then,
somebody had seen the Redford movie and noticed,
and pointed it out,
and made me feel weird about myself.
Or we could go with homage.
We're editing all this, right?
(CHUCKLES)
FILLLON: Ron,
your biggest challenge in this scene?
What were you thinking about?
GLASS: I was really
uncomfortable the Whole time.
Not that I should have
been comfortable,
but I was really
uncomfortable the whole time
because I couldn't... I didn't
know where my head was.
I didn't know... I didn't know
Where the camera was, and...
You know what I mean?
I was just like...
But then, our thing together
is what kept me
from just getting
carried away by the whole thing that t
didn't know where the hell my head was,
and all that kind of stuff,
you know? FILLLON: Mmm-hmm.
WHEDON: We could have
sold Bobblehead Books.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: You only had the sun
in your eyes for a few hours.
WHEDON: Yes, there are...
GLASS: Yes, it is weird.
FILLLON: There are moments
Where, suspended in time,
I have these fleeting
periods of... You know,
short spans of time
where I completely believe
I'm Malcolm Reynolds.
Because of the way people are looking at me,
or talking to me.
I'm buying it 100%, "Oh, my God,
I'm totally a space captain."
This scene, watching you die,
was one of those moments.
Very sad for me.
GLASS: Yeah. And I remember
it was very emotional for me, too.
WHEDON: Really?
And I remember that
Jess gave you a note
to not get overly emotional,
and I was confused by it.
WHEDON: Well, yeah.
I generally give that
note to everybody,
and I mentioned the comment
where Gina had a problem with that.
When I was like, "You got to keep it in,
you got to keep it in." She's like,
"No, I got to let it out."
And then, we're like,
"Oh, she needs to move forward
and it doesn't seem to make sense."
"Oh, she's doing it
because of grief."
I always tell people to do
less. My thing is always,
if you laugh, they won't. If you cry,
they won't. FILLLON.“ Yeah.
And every actor,
fights me on it in the same way that,
you know, I was talking about how people,
like, they want to protect themselves,
or, you know...
But again, I think that that tension is
great because I'm wrong a lot of the time.
I know that, but, like, they'll be
pulling one way, I'll be pulling another,
and somewhere in the middle, stretched out,
is gonna be where that performance ties.
FILLLON: But I know what you're talking about,
and I do agree.
I think it's far more powerful
when I see someone,
rather than when I see someone who's crying,
that I see someone
who's trying not to cry.
Who's trying to hold
it in. Who's trying...
You see there's a struggle. You see that
there's obviously something inside them
that's pouring out, or wants to pour out,
but they're holding it in.
WHEDON: Yeah.
GLASS: The weird thing... i
wasn't tempted to cry at all.
(ALL LAUGHING)
You know what I mean? t
wasn't tempted to cry at all.
But I was very concerned
that you didn't get to cry.
FILLLON: Thank you for that.
Thank you. I cried later.
GLASS: It was weird.
WHEDON: Even, you know,
his last thoughts are of someone else.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
I didn't mean it
that way, but...
No, no, no. I know What
you mean. It is, it's...
It's a weird line.
And I very often,
maybe it's 'cause I'm such a WASP,
but you know, I mean,
a lot of my actors,
the one word they've
always heard me say is "less."
Less, less, less.
Because...
Because I just... I
always wanna hold back.
And then sometimes they'll go.
The only time... I think I told
Jewel once in Objects in Space,
during the scene with Early
where he's talking about rape...
it's like,
"Give it an to me. Show me everything."
And I had never asked for that before,
and it was amazing.
That was really cool.
But generally speaking...
Also, with Mal,
it was so hard to chart
what you were gonna be.
Like, where this was taking you
emotionally. Is it deadening you?
Is it despair? is it, you know, like,
I mean, where's the next thing?
FILLLON: Is it rage? Is... I mean,
I knew Where you were going narrative/y,
but, like, how do I show
that? Because you don't...
You don't say,
"Let us rise up against to save our brother."
You say, you know, "Let's...
You know,
"Run away! Run away!"
he becomes even more...
The problem that he has that you're
trying to help him with as you're dying
doesn't get better
from your death.
It comes later.
It's not till Miranda
that he really...
So, it's sort of, you know,
I don't know Where
I need to be. Which part of his
heartbreak do I need to be charting?
It's... And because
it was my first movie,
that's a much longer journey.
And so it was much harder for me to,
sort of, figure out.
GLASS: But that was probably
one of the strongest things I ever...
That I ever felt was the
intention of trying to really
make sure that you got it
before I took out.
FILLLON: Yeah. You
had a limited span of time.
Yeah. That was really... That
was a challenge that I really loved.
I loved, you know, being in it.
And I have to say...
Who was it that braided you hair,
your niece? Yeah.
Please thank her because it made for
an excellent grip on the back of your head.
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: Which helped you with
you knowing where your head should be.
Yeah, everybody wins.
It's collaboration.
GLAU: It's teamwork.
GLASS: I think I gave her $20.
(ALL LAUGHING)
ZOE: Sir...
Just tell me when we're close.
FILLLON: There was
another scene here.
WHEDON: Yes, you and Morena,
who, as I said, suffered
much in the editing.
We actually... My favorite moment of yours,
it's in the DVD extras,
is that when you see her and
you try and get yourself together
and talk like a normal person.
This is, you know,
the moment he's not giving you,
Ron, in a way.
It's the moment he has there
and there was a little bit more of it
before he sat down with Morena.
GLASS: There was another thing
that t was also really looking forward to
with Morena, for the two of
them to be able to have, you know,
talk their language together.
WHEDON: Their connection was always
one of the sweetest things on the show to me.
Yeah.
Because, yeah, they were
the most civilized,
least agenda-filled people,
in their way.
But you know, she and Kaylee,
their relationship
was very beautiful.
They have no lines together.
They do not exchange a
sentence in the entire movie.
That's the problem with,
you know, the movie.
Is when you've created
something with nine characters
and you have two hours.
That's,
you know... l literally have her put her hand on
Jewel's shoulder at one point,
just so that they
can have interacted.
(GLASS LAUGHS)
And Jewel talks about her.
I guess they do... They speak to
each other in the postcard flashback.
But that's it.
Not once when she gets
back on board just because,
you know, it's always,
literally, cut to the chase.
FILLLON: This was
always great for me.
To show how scary Reavers are,
Jayne was terrified of them.
WHEDON: Yeah.
That always works.
There's one thing
that scares Jayne.
It's the same thing
with, you know,
when Jayne throws
his hand in and says,
"I'm ready to be heroic,"
you know everybody else is.
When Jayne's scared,
you know everybody else should be.
FILLLON: Yeah, that always
brought it home for me.
There's always
a character like that.
A Spike or Cordelia kind of
character Who's absolute.
When they go, so goes everybody.
BALDWIN: I was always trying to
figure out what Jayne's history was
with Reavers specifically.
You know, I imagined a few things,
like I'd seen him
take out some... I've seen aftermath,
of course,
but was there any,
like, personal connection
he'd had with his family or...
WHEDON: I always thought...
I didn't think it was, like,
"Reavers killed them."
Cause, you know,
his family is intact,
and the idea that Jayne
had a nice family life
was something that I thought
was sweet. It wasn't like...
BALDWIN: Suburban family life.
It's like he went into this world
because that was a viable career option
for people on his planet.
FILLLON: How was I feeling
this day, Joss?
What?
How was I feeling?
You weren't in a harness.
Yeah, but space suits, man.
I know, and a light broke,
which cost us an hour.
And I thought I was going
to get home to see my son.
I do remember because,
Adam, you were like,
"We got it?" You know,
'cause I finished up.
I really wanted to get
home and see my son,
and then we decided a thing to do,
and you're like,
"We do shoot the
movie, right?"
You got a little sad that t was
moving that quickly at that point.
It happened a couple of days Where juggling
fatherhood and filmmaking was really hard.
BALDWIN: Yeah, and I'm a jaded dad,
so it was like, you know,
"It's no big deal. It's just another
kid." You're so sick of children.
Oh, totally sick... Well,
except for this one over here.
(ALL LAUGHING)
The older ones,
they're out already.
What are those odds?
You still love your kids,
right on. Wake up.
GLASS: He did wake up
for that one.
WHEDON: Anyway, my theory,
probably Reavers were like bedtime monsters.
Like you know, "Eat your
vegetables, the Reavers..."
Like, he's always
grown up hearing about...
FILLLON: You can't pay for a special
effect to make the dress fly like that.
I know, I know. It took 14 air jets and wires,
3 lot of wires.
BALDWIN: Which high
school is this?
This is... I think
it's called Diamond Ranch.
FILLLON:
It's called Space School.
Future school. It hasn't been
built yet. Won't be built till 2007.
That was a really
interesting place.
Yeah, very funky design.
And just a few props placed in
the back of... The same props,
placed in the back of
every shot, pretty much,
got us our world.
JAYNE: They's just
sitting here.
They didn't crash.
And that was just
sticking out there.
I wanted to stick the TV on there
because I saw that sticking out there,
I'm like,
"Oh, that looks cool."
Now this you said was, Summer,
your other hardest day?
Cause you get your
big, emotional thing.
What did you do?
How did you do it?
GLAU: I'm afraid
of everybody.
That's right,
everybody in the cast is staring at you.
Yeah. I felt shy.
FILLION: And I had a plane to catch,
so I was really pressuring her.
(GLAU CHUCKLES)
WHEDON: Yeah, well, you know,
Nathan likes to put on the pressure.
I just like to go up to an actress
right before a take and say,
"Don't do that thing with
your face. And rolling."
(GLAU LAUGHS)
BALDWIN: I do another thing
that's bad continuity here, too.
I turn one way and
then turn the other.
Just to mess with continuity.
WHEDON: Oh, my God!
I loved doing the
reflection shot.
You've destroyed my
movie, Adam Baldwin.
I only did it because“.
Well, you'll see a close-up here,
I turn right,
and then when you cut back to me,
I'm turning left.
You see,
in the background there. We don't...
There he is,
turning left, you see?
Wow,
you are really paying attention to yourself.
GLASS: I missed that.
WHEDON: I was looking at
Summer that whole time.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: Oh, Summer's
in this scene, too.
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: Yeah, you had to...
GLAU: And then,
they made me switch all the Chinese in post.
Then they switched it back.
WHEDON: I know.
There were disagreements about
what the Chinese was gonna be.
And what was right.
I re-did this scene probably
six times. And you had to do
all this emotional
stuff in Chinese.
But this was another one, three takes
and we were out, sweetheart. Three takes.
Cause I did it a bunch in post.
But, no, I mean,
the stuff you accomplished you
couldn't do in post. Yeah, that was that.
I mean,
it was pretty amazing and that was, again,
part of the first two weeks
'cause it was location.
Uh-huh, I remember that.
You know, you do this
every time. You're like,
(IMITATING GLAU) "I can't
do it. I don't know how to do it."
Boom! You do it.
(IMITATING GLAU) "I don't
know if I did it. Did I do it?"
The actual doing of it
takes about 15 minutes.
GLAU: The worrying
about it is weeks.
Yeah, the worrying
FILLLON: The lovely and talented
Sarah Paulson. Where did you find her?
WHEDON: Ah, Sarah Paulson.
Um, well, Down with Love.
I was a fan from that.
Then,
I talked in the other commentary about...
That I like to hire comedians,
because if they can
do the one thing,
generally speaking,
they can do the other.
And... But, you know,
I wanted to hire her,
people were unsure.
We'd hired somebody else.
And, as you know,
we had to re-shoot it,
but we had all the camera moves
locked into a computer, so we could.
And I just kind of
fought for her,
which I didn't do
a lot of fighting,
'cause generally speaking we
were mostly all on the same page.
But I remember you watching her.
You stopped by while
she was doing her stuff.
And she made you cry.
FILLLON: Oh, my God.
It was terrifying,
listening to her.
She really let it out.
WHEDON: Yeah,
she was tremendous.
BALDWIN: is there any sort of,
overarching metaphorical, like,
message behind what she's telling
us now with this whole Pax thing?
WHEDON: I totally should've
put one of those in.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING) Ah, man. No,
obviously, she's like, you know,
the author's message woman, "Hello,
I'm author's message. Welcome to my hologram."
You know, the whole thing about
trying to stop people from fighting
will stop them from...
You know, all our basest impulses
are connected to our greatest impulses.
All our most destructive ideas are
connected to our most advanced ideas.
It's just who we are.
It's the yin and the yang, the black
and the white, and that's the whole point.
That right to be wrong.
Cause Malcolm is wrong
about almost everything.
Except one,
and one's all you need.
...beyond madness.
They have become...
No, Sarah, yeah.
She was, you know...
She was hilarious. I met with her,
and she was really fun.
And she tried on the
jumpsuit. She's like,
"Just so you know, I'm packing
an ass in this thing. I look like JLo."
(ALL LAUGHING)
That's all she said
about her costume.
She's real... Have you
worked with her at all?
FILLLON: I never worked with her,
but I've known her... I knew her for...
I've known her for some time. We
met in New York a long time ago.
I know all too well
that she's so talented.
I didn't... I mean,
this was before she did
Glass Menagerie and it's just...
You know, sort of
all over the place...
I'd seen her here and there,
but I had no idea how good
she was. She's got talent.
I watched something else.
Nip/Tuck. She was in, you know,
just for one dramatic piece.
FILLLON: It's just those
last few screams,
that's what really sends it
over the edge for me. I know.
I know, they're horrible.
They're just horrible.
And you have to
love that person.
If you don't love that person,
it all gets lost.
BALDWIN: What's the vomit?
Vomit, it's genuine catharsis.
No, I was wondering if it
was pea soup this time or if it...
Oh, well,
you asked about themes last time.
Summer, what was the vomit?
I can't remember. I think,
like, oatmeal and...
Weren't you on a
bender the night before?
Improv again. GLAU: Oh,
it was a protein shake.
Protein shake.
With oatmeal.
And you made us do
your close-up again.
Yeah, I didn't like it.
You didn't like your close-up,
and then we switched and came around,
did a whole thing.
And you were like...
(WHIMPERING)
Only, not that loud or coherent.
I'm like,
"You must speak up."
(IMITATING GLAU) "Can
we have another close-up?"
(BALDWIN LAUGHING) "Okay,
we'll come back around."
You know, 'cause we
always, you know...
Jack Green,
you're never behind. We were always doing fine.
BALDWIN: Yes, it's true.
I'm like, "We'll come back
around and get it." You're like,
(IN TIMID HIGH-PITCHED VOICE)
"Oh, no, but I don't like it."
You just... You were
so shy about asking.
And then, it was much better.
Jack lit it better,
the angle was better, the lens, just,
you looked better,
the performance was spot on.
It was great that
we came back around.
But now you're an old hand.
But you're terribly
well preserved.
But you're an old hand and you probably
wouldn't have that problem anymore.
BALDWIN: That bottle
is from Jamestown.
Oh, yeah.
Pilfered it.
I love the little strobing.
FILLLON: Wait. You stole it from
Jaynestown and brought it back for Serenity?
BALDWIN: Mmm-hmm.
Nicely done.
Thank you.
You filthy thief.
I... Totally, yeah.
Sorry, Fox.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
I carved my name
in that table, too.
Prop guy was like, "Dude,
we gotta return that table."
WHEDON: Now, do you think that
would be settled? See, the bottle!
See the bottle? FILLLON: No,
and you know What?
Listen,
here's what I wanna say about that moment.
When I was a kid and I
wanted to be in movies,
that's what I was looking for.
One of those.
WHEDON: Yeah.
Little bit of hovercraft chase,
little bit of shooting
people in the face,
little bit of that.
WHEDON: Little bit of,
"Let's just can a Spielberg a Spielberg."
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
GLASS: Talking about taking things,
or pilfering things, I tried to get...
There was a tiny little
scapular that I wore
that had... I mean,
it was just...
Probably, most people never even saw it,
you know.
On the last day, when
I was getting ready
to leave, I kept it.
And just as I was about to...
I was about to reach for the
door to open the door to go out,
there was a knock on the door
from the costume person, saying,
"Be sure to leave
the scapular."
(GLASS LAUGHING)
BA ID WIN.“ "D 'Oh! "
WHEDON: The Fox
executives are like,
"it's not enough to cancel their show.
Keep thinking, damn it! I've got an idea."
(ALL LAUGHING)
But just be thankful it wasn't like
Buffy where they asked them to
leave their costumes
and not wash them.
So they could auction them.
Pretty odd. You know what?
All of this is gonna get out out.
FILLLON: That's pretty gross.
It's going to be dead silence,
what I just said.
So, quickly,
somebody say something.
GLASS: Well, I got socks.
Well, everyone's a winner.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
Finding all the video
playback for this was really hard
because we couldn't get
the rights to anything.
That's why there's a lot of
old cartoons from, like,
pre... You know, like that. Actually,
old Superman cartoons.
FILLLON: I recognize
the animation.
And, yeah, Chris Buchanan
gathered all of that stuff
'cause he was generally
in charge of all the video.
FILLLON: This was another
bit I loved reading in the script.
It was really, you know...
After you guys left,
the effects...
Well, you know,
we went back and forth.
They took a long time to get...
How much anthropomorphism could
we get from this guy, this little ship?
And I love those red lights,
and I sort of drew them
on the blades and stuff.
It was very hard to...
You know, there's so much
visual information that they'd create.
And they'd show it to us and we'd be like,
"That's great."
"Except, we can't
see Serenity."
"You know, they'd be like, " Oh,
yeah. Right, hold it. One sec.
"We totally have
that button."
(ALL CHUCKLING)
It was, uh, you know.
It was much harder to
realize than it was to write.
Partially, I guess,
'cause I'm such a newbie.
WASH: Go! Move!
All of that, those three shots,
are all from different scenes.
Of, you know, him pushing, that's,
like, from the skiff, from the chase.
BALDWIN: What? And her, that's from
when they were worried about Reavers.
Yeah, I pulled all those
from other scenes
to understand he was going and
just to make the thing coherent.
Because there's a lot,
you know, a lot of information.
FILLLON: Boy, you really took
the magic out of this movie.
No, that... Adam did that
with his bad matching.
BALDWIN: So,
wait a minute. Mal was up on top of Serenity
and now he's... At this point,
you cut away to Chiwe
so that Mal can climb back in.
Right.
In the 190 page draft,
there was an enormous set piece
that took place as he's climbing back in
and they're chasing him, and some of
them get on, and he's firing back at them.
And there was a whole...
I mean, it was...
The $100 million,
three-hour version of this movie contained that.
FILLLON:
Let's make that movie.
Uh, okay.
BALDWIN: Yeah, he
got that suit off.
FILLLON: This I love.
WHEDON: I never...
I never don't love that.
Target the Reavers.
Target the Reavers!
Target everyone!
Somebody fire!
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
FILLLON.“ Ah, Chiwetel.
WHEDON: Seeing the operative
lose his cool is always fun.
Now, here's Alan Tudyk's
moment to shine.
Yes.
BALDWIN: And last moment.
Totally spoiled it.
FILLLON: Boy, I hope
nothing happens to him.
BALDWIN: Now, we're in space,
right? We're still like...
WHEDON: Well... FILLLON: No,
this is an atmosphere.
What we did was, we decided the
ion cloud was the end of atmosphere.
The edge of atmosphere, and this originally
was gonna play in space with no sound,
but, you know,
we got into it and we were like,
"We just need to have
all the juice we can."
You know, I always wanted
everything to be very docu and very...
You know, "Let's not admit
that it's a movie."
And then we got into it, and we were like,
"We need loud explosions, lots of music"
"and some clouds behind
them to justify it."
And in fact, you know, that's why
there's bright light on you guys at one point
from the side, that we
actually had a sun source
that we had to take out and
turn into explosions instead.
FILLLON: I have watched
this scene so many times.
Really?
What happens?
We make it in the end.
It's rough, but we make it.
BALDWIN: Alan doesn't.
I watch this a lot.
I do. I really like this.
WHEDON: It was fun.
It was so hard.
But not un-fun.
BALDWIN: And this thing
he jumps into is called a...
Tube of cardboard?
BALDWIN: Dart. Dart. Look carefully,
that's cardboard.
Oh, it is cardboard.
But I jumped in it with my brothers,
they were visiting the set that day,
and it was really fun.
But that little ship is called a Dart,
right? Yes, a Dart.
It's in the script
but you never...
Yes, we called that...
l called it a Dart,
which made sense.
Looks kind of like a dart.
Not a Dodge Dart, but...
(CHUCKLING)
That would be great
if it had fins.
FILLLON: But those are
good in space, too.
Yeah, those, they really
built them solid.
They will go in space.
Now, Summer, I remember
you and I took a day,
we went down to watch Loni crash the ship.
WHEDON: Oh, you mean at the miniatures
house? Yeah, do you remember that?
GLAU: Mmm-hmm.
WHEDON: You guys came.
That was cool.
Everybody,
strap yourselves into something!
- Jayne.
- JAYNE: Got it!
Kaylee, come on.
FILLLON: This was all
very exciting to film.
Explosions going on.
WHEDON: And we actually shook the... Yeah,
we had that on gimbals, too.
The bridge. Yeah,
the bridge. The bridge would shake.
And the galley and the dining
room are the two we had on gimbals,
so everybody was in
a place we could shake.
That's when you know
you've made it.
On the TV show,
we'd all pretend and then shake the camera.
Yeah. In the movie,
we shake the set.
BALDWIN: t wanted to spend a
little extra time buckling in Inara but...
(MEN LAUGHING)
WHEDON: He had a
monologue about it.
"You okay?
You all buckled in?"
But I love the fact, actually...
FILLION: I remember!
went in for looping,
and they wanted me to loop in
lines for Adam falling away.
And I said, "That's not me."
They go, "Are you sure?"
(ALL LAUGHING)
Pretty sure.
WHEDON: "That's not
even stunt me!"
I mean, even if you can't see the face,
you know I'm on the bridge
and that's not the bridge,
you know that.
But I like the fact that
Jayne is checking everybody.
Like, he's behaving like a soldier
there and not like a selfish son of a bitch.
I think that's cool.
And pays the price for it.
And when I'm like,
"Can you..."
You know, because I'm worried about,
again, Steadicam.
With the shaking,
we're not gonna get it.
Can you sell that it's shaky?
And then you just
went to your knees.
BALDWIN: Yeah,
I just fall down. Yeah, that sold it.
There we go, now we're
in the launchers.
BALDWIN: "Yeah, Chad,
can I have some knee pads? I'm gonna fall."
How fast are they going?
FILLLON: Ninety-eight
miles an hour. Ninety-eight?
WHEDON: 120 flemblas
per gnute.
FILLLON: "Four hundred
quatloos on the newcomer."
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
FILLLON: Why did they put
a hole in the landing spot?
WHEDON: There is a Whole
explanation for that,
with stairs in the thing,
and it's not supposed to go that far.
But the way it's shot,
you can't really tell.
I don't really care so
much about anything,
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
especially Alan.
BALDWIN: And this decision
came about how?
Well, many factors.
You know, schedules
were very difficult,
and you know, I just thought
when it occurred,
"Oh," you know.
Killing Wash. It suddenly was like,
"Oh, my God, of course."
Because then there's the
domino effect with everybody else.
I also remember Gina.
This was, you know...
When we first did this,
she was playing a
very quiet moment.
I was like,
"No, no, no. For here,"
"it's just orders."
"Get up, get up. It's not in
there yet. I don't believe it yet."
Which is why when
we got into this space,
she was like, "Well, now, I've got it.
It's in me, and I've got to get it out."
And, well, she gets it out on
that Reaver rather spectacularly.
But it was...
It was just interesting
because we came at his death
from two totally
different places.
I laughed and she just
kind of chortled.
(ALL LAUGHING)
And Alan would be like,
"My chest itches."
"I don't know why. Every time we
go to the bridge, my chest itches."
"It's a thing.
It's weird, huh?"
BALDWIN: But did you get
a lot of grief for that decision?
Oh, my God!
At one of the first
screenings that had fans in it,
I was cornered by some fans
who genuinely scared me,
and that's almost never happened. Like,
people...
They weren't big,
they weren't intimidating, they were small.
It was a couple,
and I believe they had laser vision.
FILLLON: They were burning
into you. I was just backing up,
"just going, " Look,
it's what the narrative needed,
"and I feel it's right,
and I love the character as much as you do."
And they were just like,
"No, why did you hurt us?"
It's like, you know,
I was genuinely, like,
"I think I made
a terrible mistake."
(ALL LAUGHING)
"Quick!"
But actually, you know,
as weird as that encounter was,
it only reaffirmed what I always
believe in those situations.
Clearly, I got it right.
FILLLON.“ Uh-huh.
You gotta upset people. Besides,
I have so many buy-backs.
I buy back Simon's death,
I buy back River's death,
I buy back your death, you know.
Everybody who looks
like they've...
You know, Kaylee,
it looks like one... Somebody's going out.
And because I've just killed
Wash rather unequivocally,
you can have all
those buy-backs,
and still the movie's still compelling
and you don't feel like, "Ugh."
FILLLON: It's no secret that
Joss Whedon kills characters.
No. It's no secret.
So once Ron Glass bites it,
people think,
"Oh, I guess we're safe."
Yeah, 'cause,
yeah. The work is... Joss has got his jollies.
Right.
But then after Wash dies,
it looks like we're all gonna die.
People... And Wash doesn't have a thematic,
you know.
"You go ahead," you know.
"I've learned one thing."
So, yeah, I've always... Wait,
I'm finishing my joke.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
Can't be thinking on revenge
if we're gonna get through this.
Do you really think any of
us are gonna get through this?
FILLLON: Another one of
the greatest lines in this movie.
Yes, one of the biggest lines.
I might.
Well-delivered, my friend.
Yeah, classic.
It's some of your best work.
BALDWIN: Oh, well...
WHEDON: Yeah,
we looped him with another actor, but anyway...
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
FILLLON: This was my
last day of filming.
WHEDON: Yes. Yes.
I talked in the other commentary
about how you told me about how
Mal feels about this guy.
It was one of those moments
I got really choked up.
It was towards the end of filming,
and the way you talked about him was,
"Mal likes this guy."
You know, he did
something. He tried.
FILLLON.“ Yeah.
And I just loved that so much,
and there was another one,
it was also just a couple of days before this,
with Chiwetel.
"When I'm like, " When you
leave and he's tied up
"and you've won,
should you look at him?"
And you're like,
"it's not about us anymore."
And I was just like,
"Ooh! You give me chills."
I got a short span here.
They destroyed my equipment...
BALDWIN: Hot bot. FILLLON: Yeah,
you gotta love that.
WHEDON: You know, the outfits
they showed me for her...
Yeah?
They were just...
All, like, leather,
you know, skimpy. I'm like,
"Guys, this is his wife. He's
in love. Show some respect."
They came back with
the Barbie do” stuff,
and I was in heaven.
Mid-'503 stuff. Nice.
Yeah, it worked well.
BALDWIN: Jayne liked to
name his weapons, right?
WHEDON: Yes.
There was a guy
in a TV show who did some
South Park versions of us.
Yeah.
He passed away but did
seem really cool, like...
All of us as South Park
characters, so I...
In honor of that guy's passing,
I named that big gun
that's about to go off of mine
after him.
His name's Kerry.
Kerry?
That's a great...
It's a good gun.
But the gun's name was Lux.
Oh.
In my head, but it's not,
you know... Okay.
...portrayed. Cause
you wouldn't let me.
Just like you wouldn't
let me love Inara.
I think the gun loved Inara.
And, people, the frisson
between them is incredible.
That's why we couldn't
get the PG-13 for so long.
FILLLON: Another beautiful
moment in the movie.
Yes.
This regret. This
realization and regret.
And loop lines because,
as originally scripted,
way too flowery.
Really? And when I gave
Sean the new version to loop,
he was like,
"Thank you."
Yeah, he was like... He was a man about it,
he never said anything.
But when he got the new lines he was like,
"Oh, thank God."
Cause it was just too speechy. I think he said,
"thou" at one point.
And a wonderful moment
that tells us exactly who
little Kaylee is.
Hell with this.
I'm gonna live.
Yeah, that's
a stand-up-and-cheer.
Mal. Guy killed me, Mal.
He killed me with a sword.
FILLLON: All right,
Reavers are coming.
WHEDON: That's the gun
you were talking about?
BALDWIN: Yeah. That's Lux.
The one that rolls around.
Oh, and that bow
that Morena had.
It is like a 06! bow.
FILLLON: Bow and arrow,
that's 3 CG! bow and arrow.
WHEDON: Yes.
BALDWIN: And Why?
WHEDON: Audiences laughed
at the bow and arrow.
FILLLON: You know Why? Because the
archery scene was taken out earlier in the film.
WHEDON: The archery scene...
All the stuff of her at the
training house was taken out.
And the archery didn't really work that we“,
anyway.
People were like, "Ah, looks a little,
actually, Wonder Womany."
Ironically.
So when it showed up,
people were like,
"How is that a part of her
character that she would have that?"
And they just laughed and laughed,
where it made sense to me but...
if you haven't shown it to the audience,
then you haven't shown it.
So we got ourselves a
beautiful CGI bolt shooter.
BALDWIN: Was there ever any
consideration of yours early on in the process
of how you were gonna
portray the Reavers?
Were they ever gonna have any personality?
Were they always gonna be just these...
it was always gonna be as, you know...
Zombies who can really get their groove on.
Who can move. It was just
complete animal rage.
And it was never gonna be like,
"Wow, that Reaver's
partially okay."
It was... They were
always gonna be
just an absolute force
of insane madness
to counterbalance an absolute
force of insane rationality,
which is what...
Chiwetel represented what the
blue-hand guys represented in the show.
FILLLON: Now, shooting this scene,
in my head I'm thinking to myself,
"I'm totally in a
quickdraw fight in a movie."
"I'm in a quickdraw fight
and I'm in a movie."
Wheel
(WHEDON LAUGHS)
I am.
Yeah,
a lot of dreams coming true right there, bang.
One quick little snippet.
Of course, that ain't
exactly Plan A.
Now this was the most
challenging thing I had to do
in the whole show.
Right there.
WHEDON: That jump?
That jump.
Yeah. Everything I had to do in that show,
my body said,
"Yeah, let's do that.
That'd be great."
When I went to do that my body was saying,
"Whoa! Nate, Nate, Nate."
BALDWIN: "Don't fall."
"Hey, hey, buddy.
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
"Let's think about this."
WHEDON: It does look great.
BALDWIN: Mini-Gatling gun.
Love it.
What do they call
those little balls?
WHEDON: Poop balls!
(LAUGHING) Turd balls.
Yeah. They looked like they were
made out of poop, which actually,
in Reaver terms,
makes perfect sense. But...
They were gnarly,
they had bits of metal and stuff but, yeah,
they didn't not entirely
resemble poo.
FILLLON: Of all the places to hang precariously,
a giant fan.
(LAUGHS) I know.
Now watch how close his
feet get to my hands. I know.
He doesn't care about your
hands that much. GLAU: Oh.
(GRUNTING)
BALDWIN: I remember you
talking to me about this scene.
When your face goes
splat on the glass.
FILLLON: Now everybody thinks
it's one particular point.
They think it's this
point coming up right here.
Boom! Cause they see the
marred spot. GLAU: Ooh!
WHEDON: Oh, no.
It's not that one.
FILLLON: It's not that one. That
one's good. It's the other one.
The other one was where
your face got puffy.
"I remember you telling me, " Nathan,
I want your face to hit right there.
"Can you make your face
hit right there?"
Remember that? Yeah,
I also remember you saying,
(MUMBLING) "Are we...
Did we get it?"
And I'm like,
"What's going on?"
'Cause I had no idea you
were actually hitting your face,
and we were on take six.
"And you were like... You know,
you looked like Rondo Hatten from one side."
(BALDWIN LAUGHING)
FILLLON: It was actually
doing your show, Buffy,
that I fell into frame dead,
and I fell kind of slowly
and softly and I didn't...
I was never, ever happy
with that and I thought,
"That's never gonna
happen to me again."
"I'm not gonna be unhappy with
my head hitting the ground like that."
So, yeah.
So I let it come down.
BALDWIN: I'm totally shot.
I've been shot here.
WHEDON: I know, and you
seem to be okay with it.
Yeah, being shot.
Well, I tend to, like, you know,
with Mal getting stabbed.
I tend to injure people beyond
recovery and still have them,
you know,
dancing and scratching and laughing and jumping.
Shooting some hoops.
BALDWIN: NOW I'm hurt.
FILLLON: This is where it's looking
pretty bad for pretty much everybody.
The lift isn't moving.
WHEDON: This was really tough.
This whole thing was so tough because
we were near the end. This was,
like, the last day for a lot of people.
Jack had three lighting
setups to do in this area.
Dark, darker and then
the emergency lights.
And it just... This one,
this is where it got really...
FILLLON: This scene...
. . . ugly.
I'm not gonna cry today.
SIMON: My bag.
But this scene makes
me very emotional.
Well, as is well known,
it made Summer so emotional
we could almost not
use the audio. Really?
After we did Sean's side...
GLAU: You wanted me to be quiet.
After we did Sean's side,
we had to wait till she was ready
to do her side because
she was crying so hard.
FILLLON: For a man Who's so
dedicated to his sister, he's been shot,
belly-shot,
and his thought is to apologize
to his sister,
"I'm sorry."
It kills me. It tears
me from the inside.
WHEDON: There's a certain kind of
character that is just so completely hardcore
about being decent,
and they're fictional,
obviously,
that they fascinate me.
People who just won't ever, like,
take their eyes off the prize,
that kind of insane devotion.
I love it, I think it's very...
I love the complexity of
people, but I also love
somebody who's just
gonna put that aside.
Cause it's a beautiful fantasy.
This is another
beautiful fantasy.
A girl from
an Edward Gorey drawing
defeats an entire Romero army.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
I let you wear shoes.
GLAU: Thanks.
(CHUCKLES)
FILLLON: This was, like,
second- or third-last day for me.
WHEDON: Did you finish up
in the tunnel, Summer?
I finished with... We finished on the bridge,
didn't we?
That was our last day?
FILLLON: That was our
last day together,
but I finished in that room
with David Krumholtz.
80... Oh, yeah. I remember,
I came that day.
WHEDON: You came
the last day. Yes!
Possibly had a little champagne!
Loni gave it to us.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: Gut-stabbed.
GLAU: Loni brought it
to the makeup trailer.
WHEDON: You looked so upset.
Chiwetel and I were singing
Merrily We Roll Along in our chairs,
and you were standing there
looking very upset.
And I was like,
"What's wrong?" You're like,
(WHISPERING)
"I've had champagne."
I'm like, "Nobody's gonna notice,
except that you've told everybody."
FILLLON: You're miked.
It was.
You suppose he got through?
I... You know,
if there had been 63 days of shooting...
Slight coma.
Probably 'cause you can see the
finish line. I got pretty wrung out.
FILLLON: You were working
pretty hard, man.
That's the one we were
talking about. That's the one.
That's the one that made
your face all puffy.
"And I was like, " If! had known
you were doing something like that,
"I totally would've gotten a
shot with your puffy face."
I would have used it.
All subsequent shots were
shots of my puffy face.
Well, yeah,
but your puffy face is on the other side.
You've done remarkable things.
FILLLON:
Those were insert shots.
Good thing the villain doesn't talk
too much. It gave the hero an opening.
At least he doesn't think
the hero has an opening.
I know.
Now this was supposed to
be breaking his arms.
And everybody thought
he was breaking his back.
Yeah, I don't understand that.
You're not watching enough WWF if
you think that's breaking someone's back.
GLAU: Who chose that?
Was that Chad?
WHEDON: I think so, I think
Chad came up with that.
FILLLON: I think it's
completely reasonable.
You do believe he's out of the
game once you hear that noise.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm sure we had to soften the noise,
probably, for the rating but...
FILLLON: What's his name?
I can't remember. Keith DeCandido,
who did the novelization,
did something interesting as
far as the mental processes of...
WHEDON: You read the novelization?
Oh, absolutely.
Chiwetel's process is that
he's been so well trained
that he fights so
very, very well,
that he can't take a punch.
And when he's hit,
he's quite unprepared.
Doesn't really know what to do.
Well, it's also a throat hit,
which I saved,
because throat hits are so devastating.
Yes. You know,
let you guys duke it out old school,
and then just... If he
gets one in the throat,
yeah, that's something
he's unprepared for.
The environment is stable.
FILLLON: And I got to
put in my two cents.
These little stairs are awesome,
the way they move under my feet.
Yeah.
BALDWIN: Now, the sword missed
his liver when it impaled him, right?
WHEDON: Yeah, it did,
or they brought an extra liver.
They just have livers
lying around.
In the future,
livers come cheap.
FILLLON: Space liver.
BALDWIN: Spliver.
Splivers.
WHEDON: Um, this...
You know, this is
the style of fighting
that my wife refers to as
"the only real style of fighting,"
which is to just
keep waving things.
(ALL LAUGHING) Just
keep waving things around
until they are all dead.
And by George, it works.
GLAU: It worked.
I mean, there's a little more...
There's a lot more
precision to it than that.
But there is an element
of, you know,
Danny Kaye and the
court jester of,
"Just keep going
until he goes away!"
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
FILLLON: There 's
that scream again.
Yeah, I know.
The elevator to nowhere.
Yeah, we're coming to
the big, old shot,
which was a one-taker,
which is good,
because replacing that wall
would have been a nightmare.
Right.
BALDWIN: How did you get your eye
all bloody like that? Is that a contact lens?
FILLLON: Oh,
yeah. That was a contact lens. Yeah.
That was creepy.
WHEDON: Yeah,
we had to... That blood we had to take way down.
FILLLON: Beautiful shot.
WHEDON: Entire set
designed for that shot.
And then, Jack. The light.
The half-light on her face.
Forget about it.
FILLLON: (WHISPERING)
There's someone behind you.
WHEDON: There's a doll
coming out of that.
FILLLON: That's a great shot.
GLAU: Really? I didn't
know. WHEDON: Yes.
There's a figurine coming out
of her on the Reavers
with the axes.
I'm getting me one.
SOLDIER: Do we
have a kill order?
Do we have an order?
BALDWIN: What's his
inner monologue right now?
WHEDON: What to do? What
to do? GLAU: I need a vacation.
"I can't reach my comm
control to tell them to call it off."
"My arms, or possibly
my back, is broken."
GLAU: "Oh, my back."
"Something hurts.
I don't feel good."
WHEDON: Now, this was the first day,
coming up, for a lot of you guys.
FILLLON: Yes, this was. I
remember the long bus ride out there.
GLAU: So beautiful. Playing
tunes on Adam's guitar.
WHEDON: We sang some songs.
BALDWIN: And what
was that stupid...
FILLLON: The "Morena's is so stupid,"
"she gets by on her looks,
but she's not that pretty" song?
(LAUGHING) Yes!
WHEDON: I wasn't on the bus with
you guys and I'm still sad that I missed it.
BALDWIN: Then we played... What was
it? That little electronic game? Password?
FILLLON: Oh, Catch Phrase.
Catch Phrase.
We were playing
Catch Phrase like crazy.
BALDWIN: Borrego Springs.
WHEDON: I mean,
it took all day to get here and back,
but we only needed to shoot for,
like, 45 minutes,
because it was all MOS,
all silent.
FILLLON: It was
a great first day.
That was the day I got to,
kind of, just look around
and see everybody as
their characters again.
"It's like, " Oh, you know what?
"It's nice to see my friends all
the time 'cause I see them..."
It was Jewel's first
day, I know.
But the crew I hadn't seen in
so long and it was really nice...
In all of you, I have
two friends, you know.
BALDWIN: There's the cigar bit that pays off,
kind of, in my head.
WHEDON: Yeah, I know. FILLION: Ron,
your biggest challenge in that scene?
(ALL LAUGHING) BALDWIN:
Besides the dead thing.
(GLASS LAUGHING)
WHEDON: He had to look pleased
and over his shoulder.
Um, it was tough.
This was a very important shot.
It establishes that she's above Kaylee so
that when her face comes into frame tater,
you'll know why.
You know, nothing
like an incest joke.
BALDWIN: Serenity.
WHEDON: Ah, the blue, blue sky...
That we hung behind you because
we couldn't afford an actual sky.
FILLLON:
Sean "The Bod" Maher.
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: Twenty takes.
BALDWIN: Finally, you two!
GLAU: 20 takes.
WHEDON: I never rehearsed
it 'cause I thought it's kissing,
I felt awkward
about rehearsing it,
and then I was like,
"Should have rehearsed it."
Cause it's...
It's very specific.
You have to be very
specific with that stuff.
FILLLON: And Summer
watching, just creepy.
(ALL LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: And smelling.
WHEDON: Yeah. River wants to
know everything about everyone,
and that's all I'm gonna say.
FILLLON: They have that clever
device that spins in front of the lens
to keep water off of it?
Yeah, that's right.
Perhaps the loudest
machine in the world.
(LAUGHING) I know!
I know,
but you didn't really talk much with the lens...
And you sprayed me when I was
giving notes to Chiwetel, didn't you?
I which?
You sprayed me.
For part of the scene that got cut,
I was giving notes to Chiwetet,
and I was standing and you just took
the little thing, gave me a little spray.
Good times. Yeah.
Just so I'd remember
who's captain and who's not.
(FILLLON GIGGLING)
BALDWIN: 80 about how much time
has passed here? A month, six months?
WHEDON: Well, you've built
the ship up completely
and you're all totally
healed from your wounds,
so I say it's probably,
like, three days.
(ALL LAUGHING)
Um, I always imagined
it as about a month.
There is nothing left to see.
I sort of pull a
little fast into this.
FILLLON: This was the
scene that I had no idea
what it was about until
you told me that day.
WHEDON: Yeah, yeah,
which always made me laugh,
'cause you were so
precise about meaning,
and then you were, like,
"This about what now?"
(LAUGHING) Just
something I missed.
It's tough, too.
'Cause, again, the dialogue,
"She'll fly true."
That's a hard thing to
say and not sound hokey.
And Gina... Unless
you're talking about her.
Yeah. She's got
a lot of dignity.
She's got all the dignity. In fact,
none of you guys had any 'cause she took it.
BALDWIN: I don't want dignity. All right,
Ron, you had a little.
FILLLON: I'm sorry, man. You had
great arms in that show and everything
but you ran a close second
to Gina Torres' pipes.
Ready to get off this heap,
back to civilized life?
I, uh...
BALDWIN: Actually, I ended up with
food on my face. That's all I wanted.
WHEDON: Yeah,
the food was great!
The food was full
of Chinese noodles.
Good answer.
WHEDON: I don't not love
that line, really.
This is the part
we were talking about.
FILLLON: Yeah, there was an adjustment
on one of the fallen dinosaurs there.
Summer, your thoughts
on this scene?
Last chance.
I liked the raining part.
Where it was raining.
The rain was really nice.
It really felt like it.
It was kind of cold.
FILLLON: I know for a fact that Summer
had designs on being the captain.
I still do.
WHEDON: "First,
I learn to fly it."
Just evil.
All she ever was.
But I'm saving that
for the sequel.
You know what the
first rule of flying is?
Well, I suppose you do,
since you already know what I'm about to say.
WHEDON: Well, looks like
we're winding down.
FILLLON: We are. We 're
Winding down. All in all...
GLASS: I'd have been
a good captain.
Oh, Ron.
I would.
You can learn all the
math in the 'verse,
but you take a boat in
the air that you don't love...
(ALL LAUGHING)
FILLLON: All in all, I'd have to say,
the TV series and the film,
very, very good experience.
I learned a great deal,
I had an amazing time,
I've acquired many awesome
friends for which my life is richer.
WHEDON:
And I met you guys, too.
Bittersweet.
It's bittersweet.
Like that chocolate that's dark.
You know what? I always say that,
but I'm all over the bitter.
Yeah. All the
bitter's gone for me.
I don't live by it
but I can access it.
(FILLLON LAUGHING)
BALDWIN: I always try to keep
this in the mind of redemption.
That we made something good
and we finished with something good.
And you can't control
the audience.
FILLLON: Thank you.
(ALL LAUGHING)
WHEDON: That's it.
BALDWIN: Well,
that'll be all, guys.
We went through it and now
we're through it and it's through.